<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on Aniruddha Deb</title>
    <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on Aniruddha Deb</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 15:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Maneuvers and the Oberth Effect</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/orbital-oberth/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/orbital-oberth/</guid>
      <description>Once a rocket is in orbit, if it needs to change it&amp;rsquo;s orbit (either from a lower to a higher orbit, or from a circular to an elliptical orbit), it needs to execute an Orbital Maneuver. This is accomplished by using a small impulse from thrusters to change the tangential velocity, and hence slip into a different orbit as a consequence.
Types of Orbital Maneuvers There are two types of orbital maneuvers: the Hohmann transfer orbit and the Bi-elliptic transfer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leadership, among many other things</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 23:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/leadership/</guid>
      <description>Gazettale, BSP&amp;rsquo;s premier interhostel competition, for which our team worked day and night, recently released the final standings.
And we&amp;rsquo;re fifth.
Pop the champagne and dance, team, for we&amp;rsquo;re fifth!
Jokes aside, I&amp;rsquo;m lukewarm about the result. Proud of what a ragtag bunch of people came together and assembled in the span of around two weeks, but simultaneously disappointed for not reaching the lofty expectations we set of ourselves. Hindsight is 20/20 and often very saddening, for there is seldom joy in finding out what you couldn&amp;rsquo;t see earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Habits and Badminton</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/badminton-habits/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/badminton-habits/</guid>
      <description>Atomic Habits probably needs no introduction, and neither will I bore you with one. All I&amp;rsquo;ll say is that I found a friend in hostel with a copy of the book, and when I went home, I found a physical copy on my Dad&amp;rsquo;s bookshelf (all of us have kindles, and only buy hardcopies of books that we really want a hardcopy of).
So What&amp;rsquo;s the fuss about Like it&amp;rsquo;s predecessors, Atomic Habits preaches more of the same old myelination tricks</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Knights and Knaves</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/knights-and-knaves/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 21:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2022/knights-and-knaves/</guid>
      <description>Once every year, when the sun beats down
Students here become clowns
They think on their command, people will fall
But truly, they&amp;rsquo;re just bricks in the wall
Misled by the mirage of power
Led astray till they flounder
&amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re barely 20! What do you think will change
When you become Secretary, like others who&amp;rsquo;ve aged&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you! Here&amp;rsquo;s my manifesto:
It says I&amp;rsquo;m great with a budget
I&amp;rsquo;m smart, hardworking, and totally not a puppet</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updates on Life in general</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/updates-on-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 21:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/updates-on-life/</guid>
      <description>I haven&amp;rsquo;t done one of these in a year or so (this was the previous one), and neither have I written content exclusively for my blog for atleast a few months now, so it&amp;rsquo;s a good time to do one of these because a lot has changed in the past one year.
Let&amp;rsquo;s start with summer The past two months have been amazing.
That doesn&amp;rsquo;t even sum up just how great they&amp;rsquo;ve been.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How it Happened</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/how-it-happened/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 13:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/how-it-happened/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Baba, I got Mathematics and Computing Dual at IITD&amp;rdquo;, I told my father excitedly on the day the first round allocations were over. &amp;ldquo;It probably won&amp;rsquo;t change now&amp;rdquo;. Certain of this, I returned back to whatever I was doing, excitedly waiting for the seat allocations to get over (while simultaneously crossing my fingers for the slightest hope of a branch upgrade, as we all do). Even though the campus was not opening and the semester was planned to be conducted online, I hoped to truly enjoy my first year of college life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This summer</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/this-summer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 20:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/this-summer/</guid>
      <description>What is a dream? all of us think of dreams as abstract ideals, far removed from reality, that we should chase with all the effort we can muster every day.
Meditating on this a bit more, does this make sense? What is achieved by chasing an ideal when you can never reach it? also, what would you do if you reached the ideal? Would you just stop? Life would lose all it&amp;rsquo;s meaning, and the only place to go then would be out of a tall window.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Last Time</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/last-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 14:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/blog-port/articles/2021/last-time/</guid>
      <description>Soft sunlight streaked in through the curtains, illuminating the room in a warm glow. Of course, I noticed none of that. The only thing I was aware of was my phone&amp;rsquo;s alarm clock ringing. After drowsily hitting the snooze button, I realized that I had done this twice already, so I started scrolling through the notifications. It was 8:30, and my friends were abuzz with excitement. &amp;ldquo;Oh! The JEE Advanced results are coming out today!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
