<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Aniruddha Deb - General</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/feeds/general.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aniruddhadeb.com/</id><updated>2023-07-29T19:50:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Intern Ashes</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2023/intern-ashes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-07-29T19:50:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-29T19:50:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2023-07-29:/articles/2023/intern-ashes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gardens of Versailles" src="/articles/2023/res/versailles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[If you haven't read the previous article in this series, check out 
&lt;a href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2023/intern-ignition.html"&gt;Intern Ignition&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the weekends of my internship, and in the days that followed, I got to tour 
Europe a bit. What follows is a small travelogue of my experiences in these
two months&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href='#footnote-1'&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/articles/2023/res/center_captions.css"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stroopwaffel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optiver gave …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gardens of Versailles" src="/articles/2023/res/versailles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[If you haven't read the previous article in this series, check out 
&lt;a href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2023/intern-ignition.html"&gt;Intern Ignition&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the weekends of my internship, and in the days that followed, I got to tour 
Europe a bit. What follows is a small travelogue of my experiences in these
two months&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href='#footnote-1'&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/articles/2023/res/center_captions.css"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stroopwaffel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optiver gave us a goodie bag when we arrived, and among other things, it 
contained a box of Stroopwaffel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gardens of Versailles" src="/articles/2023/res/stroopwaffel.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stroopwaffel are really thin waffles filled with caramel, and they taste
amazing! The bag was also filled with other things to see and do in Amsterdam, 
and in typical college student fashion, I did none of those. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;No Tulips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All but one of my IITD batchmates got away to see the Tulips when they landed,
and for good reason: Sunday was the last day Keukenhof would be open! 
Unfortunately my flight was delayed by an hour and even ignoring the jetlag and 
fatigue, it was not something I wanted to do after a 9-hour flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that hits you is that Amsterdam is windy. I don't mean 'stiff breeze'
windy, I mean upturn-your-umbrella windy. And chilly. The only way to stay warm 
is to have a good jacket or stay in the sunlight. Which there's a lot of, 
considering sunset happens at 9:30-10:00 PM in the summers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did was walk down for lunch. Europe is beautiful as long as
your eyes don't look at the ground: beautiful trees, lot of greenery, very
walkable roads with wide sidewalks for both cycles and people and large
well-marked crosswalks. Looking down, you're greeted with the umpteen butts of
cigarettes people stamp out. It's truly a luxury to be able to smoke: if
breathing the air doesn't eventually kill you, why don't you do it a favour and
speeden up the process?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another beautiful thing about Europe is the road rules. The first three crossings
I waited at all had the cars come to a stop and gesture me to cross. It was only
at the fourth crossing, a small cycle-lane that this sweet old grandma slowed 
down and said in English, "You have the way!". Wow, I didn't know that! Thank
you, kind granny!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only after getting back to my room and googling did I realize that pedestrians
have the way everywhere: pedestrians &amp;gt; cycles &amp;gt; cars in Amsterdam. Amazing. The
only bad thing about this is that I would have to unlearn this in India, and not
doing so would be fatal. Quite literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But enough about rules. Let's go somewhere!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Den Haag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first weekend getaway was The Hague (&lt;em&gt;Den Haag&lt;/em&gt; in Dutch), and it seemed
like a quieter, less crowded version of Amsterdam. The Netherlands is a tiny 
country, and insanely well-connected by rail: you can go from one end to
another in less than 2 hours, and the trains themselves are incredible. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After arriving, We grabbed an early-morning sausage roll from the Albert Heijn
at the station and strolled aimlessly through the streets early in the morning,
deciding where to go. The first stop was Madurodam. How tourist-y!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="madurodam" src="/articles/2023/res/madurodam.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would have assumed Madurodam is an amusement park, if not for the infographic
about it being a war memorial at the start. It was made in memory of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Maduro"&gt;George
Maduro&lt;/a&gt;, a Dutch war hero. It's an 
amazing park, and even at 9 AM in the morning, it was overrun by Gujarati 
tourists. An interesting distinction I noticed was that the Gujarati
tourists would take pictures of anything and everything, including themselves
while the European tourists were just chilling with their partners and children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madurodam also reminded me of the Doraemon episode where Suneo went to Holland
on a tour, and boasted about it to everyone. He also unfortunately lost his
camcorder there. Nobita goes to Doraemon and says that he wants a Holland tour
too. Doraemon comes up with a gadget that shows them scenes of any place in the
world live, and he invites all his friends to his home. As Doraemon shows them
the scenes in Holland (Madurodam, canals etc), Suniyo sulks while Nobita is
very happy. Soon, they come across a bench with a camcorder on it and they zoom
in, and it turns out it's Suneo's camcorder. Suneo leaps at the camcorder, only
to punch a hole through Nobita's sliding door and break the gadget, and not get
his camcorder back. &lt;strike&gt;If you know this episode's name and have a link to it, 
please let me know; Google is clueless and ChatGPT hallucinates&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: This is Season 6, Episode 34 (No. 778), &lt;a href="https://anime.stackexchange.com/questions/68178/doraemon-episode-where-suneo-goes-to-holland-on-tour"&gt;The Sight Seeing Window&lt;/a&gt;.
The original Japanese version is &lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/doraemon-1979-994-stories/Doraemon+(1979)+-+JP+RAW/TV+Anime/Doraemon+(1979)+-+Story+0778+(EX-CS2).mp4"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
while a dubbed Hindi version can be found &lt;a href="https://www.dailymotion.com/video/x8mau7o"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next stop after Madurodam was the Beach! We didn't step into the water because
it was super cold for May, and the beach was mostly empty as well. We walked 
around (under?) the pier, took some pictures and enjoyed the breeze. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="beach" src="/articles/2023/res/hague_beach.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Cold water, colder wind&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next stop after that was Escher in het Paleis (Escher in the Palace). An 
interesting thing about European culture is that they believe you when you tell 
them you're students: I wasn't asked to prove this explicitly (ok, maybe at the
Antwerp museum and the Vatican Museum). Everywhere else, it was basically a free
pass. Back on topic: Escher in the Palace was definetly the highlight of this
trip, and probably the best museum experience I've had. It was slow-moving, 
you could take your time with the portraits, get as close as you wanted to and
most of them were originals! My first brush with Escher was on the screensavers
of the nook I used to own back when I was a kid, and it was amazing to finally
see all of his work up close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="eye" src="/articles/2023/res/escher_eye.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Eye (M.C. Escher, 1946)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ants" src="/articles/2023/res/escher_ants.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mobius strip II (M.C. Escher, 1963)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ants" src="/articles/2023/res/escher_fishes.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Circle limit III (M.C. Escher, 1959). Inspired by the structure of &lt;a href="https://personal.math.ubc.ca/~cass/coxeter/r.html"&gt;Coxeter Groups&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after, we dropped down to the city center for lunch and took the train to 
our next stop that evening&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rotterdam&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rotterdam is the more modern cousin of Amsterdam, who always wears trackpants
and mirrored sunglasses. Rotterdam is filled with skyscrapers that you need to 
crane your neck to look at, and amazing bridges. It's a shame, then, that their
metro system doesn't support using credit cards, and that you need to buy a 
ticket using WiFi. Since we had exhausted our mobile data and my battery was 
near-dead, we totally did not travel on that tram without a ticket. Believe me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="erasmus bridge" src="/articles/2023/res/rotterdam.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Erasmus bridge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="euromast" src="/articles/2023/res/euromast.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Euromast&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only places we got a chance to visit here were Erasmusbrug and Euromast. We 
dropped down to a bar just below Erasmusbrug and asked them for a glass of tap 
water, and they obliged :) refreshed, we then walked across Erasmusbrug and 
back. There was a small section of the bridge that was filled with locks: couples
would add a lock to a rung to signify their love wouldn't break until the lock
did. Cute concept &amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After walking back, we took the tram to Euromast. There were two tickets: one 
that took you to the observation deck, and one that would seat you in a torus and 
take you all the way up the mast. Going up to the observation deck is good enough,
because there's a huge line that loops all the way around for going up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rotterdam" src="/articles/2023/res/euromast_view.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The view from the observation deck&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Euromast, since everything was closing down, we sat in the park next to 
it in the setting sun for 30 minutes, enjoying the breeze and nature. Soon after,
we boarded the train back to Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Zandvoort&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Belgium weekend, sometime in June when the sun was more abundant with 
it's gifts, we visited Zandvoort beach to surf. With high hopes, we entered the
surf shack to rent some equipment, only to find out that their instructor had
just come out of the water because of no waves. We were advised to pass till 
there were more waves or come back on a later day :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we did the next best thing: went and waded in the water :) after half an 
hour of wading in the waves (the water was too shallow to swim), we came out 
and lay on the beach, soaking in the sun&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href='#footnote-2'&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
Then we had some ice-cream, dried up and set off for the circuit. The circuit 
had a Classic Car Grand Prix underway, and the roars of the engines could be 
heard all the way from the beach. Since it was almost over, we managed to get
in without tickets (like the amateur backpackers we were), and when we reached,
it was truly a sight to see and hear. What followed was ten minutes of our
ears being ripped off our head. Classic cars = Big roaring V12's and V10's = 
Lots of sound. It was pure petrolhead bliss to sit there and hear those beasts
roar around the circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post-race podium featured a procession of the cars that participated, and 
there were also some classic beauties parked around the paddock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Lancia" src="/articles/2023/res/lancia.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Henri Toivonen's Lancia 037&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ferrari" src="/articles/2023/res/wolfgang_trips_ferrari.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Wolfgang von Trips' Ferrari 156 'sharknose'&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then took the train back to Haarlem, then the bus from Haarlem back to 
Amsterdam. I had marinated some Chicken with the hopes of making Tandoori, and
the other folks bought some pizza/pasta from the nearby store. We then chilled
in my room, watching F1 Qualifying and cooking / eating Tandoori Chicken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tandoori" src="/articles/2023/res/tandoori_chicken.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Amsterdam&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Amsterdam" src="/articles/2023/res/amsterdam.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amsterdam itself is an amazing city, and like every city-dweller, I didn't visit
the tourist spots in the city itself. I've heard that the Rijksmuseum is very
good, as is the Van Gogh Museum. Several other interns also went to the Heineken
Experience, but I don't drink so that was off the cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My routine in Amsterdam mostly boiled down to cycling to work, working, cycling
back and then going for a stroll along the canal nearby. I stayed at 
Wibautstraat, and I would walk a kilometre or two along the canal most days, 
enjoying the breeze and the scenic beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parks are also great places to visit, and most weekends were 
spent either staying in and working on something fun, cooking and enjoying
the sun in the park nearby. We also took a Mokumboot on the canals one day with
a bunch of snacks for a couple of hours, and it was great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Waffles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="waffles" src="/articles/2023/res/waffles.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We visited Belgium on one of the weekends: the plan was to stay over at Antwerp
for a night, but our BnB host had a water infiltration and we got to know of
this only after we had already boarded the bus to Antwerp. In typical undergrad
fashion, we decided to take things as they come and deal with this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bus dropped us off close to the city center, and the first thing we did 
was grab some waffles and stroll along the coast. We came across a small fort 
on the coast. Then realizing the Museum Aan de Stroom was close by, we continued
to walk along that street, reaching MAS in 10 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mas" src="/articles/2023/res/mas.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Museum aan de Stroom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MAS is beautifully constructed; the windows are along the staircase / floors
internally that take you up the building, and every floor is dedicated to one 
aspect of Antwerp: the port, the people, Belgium, and so on. It feels very much
like a classical museum, but this also makes it a bit boring to be inside of. 
The MAS is capped off with an observation deck, which gives you a 360-degree 
view of Antwerp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="antwerp" src="/articles/2023/res/antwerp.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Antwerp from the top of MAS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We left MAS and then decided to visit the Port authority building. Not 
realizing that it's huge, and that it's farther than it looks, our strategy of
walking in the direction of the building was a) exhausting, and b) frusturating. 
We finally opened Google maps to see that it was a decently long walk (~3 km) 
to the building. Not giving up, we started walking and finally made it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only to find out that it's closed on Saturdays. It's anyway a government
building, so they wouldn't have let us in. Sour grapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Port Authority Building" src="/articles/2023/res/zaha_hadidplein.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Port Authority Building. Designed by Zaha Hadid.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this walk, we had little time to spend, and the prospects of rooming up
with the other group visiting Brussels were also growing slim, so we decided to
take the afternoon bus back to Amsterdam. We then came back to the city centre
and looked around the Cathedral and Grotemarkt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="grotemarkt" src="/articles/2023/res/grotemarkt.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Grotemarkt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was followed by Lunch and some Belgian chocolate shopping, after which we
took the subway to the bus stop and took the bus back to Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Post Internship&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had booked my return flight on sixth noon, which gave me four and a half days 
to backpack across Europe. This was as close to &lt;em&gt;Zindagi na Milegi Dobara&lt;/em&gt; as 
I'll get to in my life: being a young twentysomething in Europe, with enough 
money to backpack across it, and having friends to do it with won't happen
every year, after all :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to take care of my luggage first. Fortunately, Schiphol Airport will store 
your luggage for you at a reasonable cost of €9 per 24 hours per bag. After 
lugging my one suitcase down to the luggage hold with a friend, all we had to 
do was board the night bus to Paris!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Crepes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="crepe" src="/articles/2023/res/crepe.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paris smells sweetly smoky. It's the same smell as the scented cigarettes
everyone smokes so fashionably, just softer. Paris Bercy-Seine bus stop, 
however, smells of pee as well. It's worse than an Indian train station when 
it comes to sanitation. It was also raining when we arrived at 6 AM, and having
to wait there for an hour and twenty minutes for a friend to arrive was &lt;em&gt;the 
most romantic introduction to the city of romance a romantic could dream about&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After regrouping, we went to the Metro. I won't launch into a full-fledged rant 
about the metro (have saved that for later), but Paris uses these arcane ticket-
checking machines that won't accept your card. We took a day-pass for the metro,
and then had breakfast at McDonalds (the quantity wasn't great).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it was still drizzling, the first plan of action was to get out at Charles
de Gaulle and roam around Central Paris a bit. We visited the Tuilleries Gardens
first, then since the Louvre was close by, we saw it from the outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Louvre" src="/articles/2023/res/louvre.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Louvre from outside. The line to go in had a one hour delay, and needed tickets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't remember what the plan after that was, but our bags were too heavy and 
the rain was as well, so we went to the nearest metro station and checked in 
our luggage at the hotel. The hotel was in a nice spot, so we left and strolled
through the streets of Paris. They were quite narrow, and uphill at times. With
the help of Google maps, we finally managed to come to this beautiful building&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pantheon" src="/articles/2023/res/pantheon.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pantheon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that we dropped down to a Japanese place nearby for lunch, and then 
went back to strolling. We walked across some bridges on the Seine, and then 
past the Notre-Dame, which was still being reconstructed. Then we went to the 
Palais Garnier via metro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Garnier Palace" src="/articles/2023/res/palais_garnier.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Palais Garnier, Ballroom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Palais Garnier was... Palatial, for lack of a better adjective. It adjoined
the Opera, and had these amazing balconies where people were mostly clicking
pictures. There was also an Opera Exhibit nearby, where they showed costumes 
that the actors at the Opera wore. It's a very short trip around the palace,
and well worth the time we spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ver-sai&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing we had done after arriving was book tickets to the Palace of 
Versailles for 4:30 PM, and after getting out of the Palais Garnier and going to 
the station in a rush, we scrambled to find and board the train to Versailles.
Surprisingly it wasn't very crowded, and we made it in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon reaching the train station at Versailles, the palace itself isn't very far.
It's about a 10-minute walk. Going in was seamless, although the crowds are 
quite thick. What followed was a walkthrough of the palace which was completed
in around half an hour. People were also shuffling forward at a decently fast
pace, not stopping for too long to examine the art, but I did manage to get some 
pictures of the ceilings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mural" src="/articles/2023/res/versailles_ceiling.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mural on the ceiling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hall of mirrors was probably the only thing I really remember. Not only 
because of the historical significance of the room, but also because the 
mirrors seemed slightly oxidized and not too bright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mirrors" src="/articles/2023/res/mirrors.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Can confirm, the hall of mirrors does have mirrors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We soon got out, and wanted to see the Gardens of Versailles. First of all, the
ticket to the palace does not give you entry to the gardens: those need a 
separate €10 ticket. Secondly, we came out around 5:05 PM, and when we got in 
the queue, the attendant repeately told us that the gardens close at 5:30, and 
that taking the ticket was not worth it. Quite a few people left the queue at 
that point, but we stuck around because we weren't going to come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was it worth it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="gardens" src="/articles/2023/res/gardens.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hell yes. We speedran the gardens, which were probably more impressive than the
palace itself. They're absolutely enormous, occupying about twice or thrice the 
area of the palace (if you couldn't make out from the picture above). They're
also immaculately maintained. There was also a fountain show, but it ended soon 
after we reached. After taking some more pictures, we left for the station, 
making it out of the gardens on time. A short dinner at the KFC near the station 
followed, after which we took the train back to Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pah-ree at night&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We soon got off the train at Paris and had to take a metro with a 
switch-over to reach our hotel. Paris has the worst metro system of any city I
have been to. It's a bunch of matchboxes on tyres (yes, rubber tyres) hurtling
at insane speeds through metre-wide tracks strewn across the city like a kitty
that clawed through it's ball of yarn. You can't even go from one matchbox to
the other, because the carriages are not connected internally. Buses and trams
were also closed when we were in the city because of the riots, and the entire
populace decided to use the metro on Saturday Night. It was breathtaking, as in
my breath was literally taken away after being squeezed among people. Peak
Delhi Metro rush has got nothing on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finally made it to the Eiffel Tower in one piece. There was a woman who had
married the Eiffel Tower&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href='#footnote-3'&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and it's easy
to see why. It's truly a thing of beauty, especially at night when it's lit up.
It lights up slowly at sunset, going from a dull red to a bright yellow, almost
as if the cast iron beams were put in an induction furnace. And if it couldn't
get any better, It bursts into sparkles at 11 PM in the night,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eiffel tower viewing was followed by Crepes at a store nearby: The crepe
maker took his time with the crepes, pouring the dough only when they were 
ordered and never making them en masse. He used a thin squeegee, the kind used 
to wash windows to make them. While the crepes were amazing, I still think my 
mother makes better and flatter &lt;em&gt;dosas&lt;/em&gt; with her &lt;em&gt;ultana&lt;/em&gt; than the crepe maker
made with his sophisticated tooling :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following day, we had to set off to the airport for our flight to Napoli. 
Breakfast at the hotel was just 3 euros, but it was the best croissant I've 
eaten in my life. It was super soft, and the pastry was not flaky at all. It was 
also very hollow on the inside, so you could tear it in half and stuff it with 
butter and jam. It's a shame I realized on the last day just how good Parisian
Croissants are, and I would've loved to try out a &lt;em&gt;boulangerie&lt;/em&gt; if I had more 
time&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href='#footnote-4'&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;To Paris, with Love&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did notice a few things while in Paris: The person from whom we brought the 
Eiffel tower souvenir was Black, the person whose cart we approached first 
to grab a crepe was Turkish, and the person serving breakfast at our hotel was
Indian. This makes Paris seem like a very diverse city, but when you notice
that every single person selling Eiffel tower souvenirs was black and every
single cart-owner was Turkish, things look a bit darker (no pun intended). It's 
the sort of thing that won't strike you, until you have friends and family tell 
you that Paris was being rocked by the most violent riots since 2005, after 
a policeman shot dead a boy of color for a traffic offence. Then, the invisible
walls between people become all too clear, and the homogenity breaks down. I 
was fortunately unaffected by the riots, but I pray that things change for the 
better as soon as possible, and that the people of the city of love learn 
to love each other for who they are rather than how they look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pasta&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="pasta" src="/articles/2023/res/pasta.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after Paris, we flew down to Napoli. We had booked a room here for three
nights, and I was looking forward to warmer climates and more beaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Napoli&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The area around Napoli Centrale is very well-maintained. It's only when you
walk down a few steps do you come to the suburbs, and find the dumpsters piled 
full of trash, plaster peeling off buildings and both the police and the army 
stationed opposite the bus stop across the street. Yikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Napoli reminded me of North Delhi. Kind people, not-so-great infra, and
crossing roads by waving your hand in front of cars (A skill I've mastered). 
There's a little spark of life behind every street corner: the children playing,
the old men and women sitting at the cafe, the wives drying clothes on the 
small balconies. It almost felt like I was transported back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public transportation in Napoli is a mess, the steets are wide, car-centric and
prone to traffic jams, so we walked 2.5 kilometers to get to the bay. We then
dropped down to a pizza joint nearby to grab some Pizza, and this was the best
pizza I've ever eaten, no question. It felt homely, lively, not overloaded with
cheese or toppings and with just enough crunch on the base. I finished that
pizza entirely, having skipped lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pompeii&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan for the next day was to head to Pompeii in the morning, and the beach
in the afternoon. We took the train to Pompeii from Napoli, and after a short 
walk reached the ruins. Do book your tickets in advance, as there are a lot of 
tour guides asking for high prices. And don't buy any hats or trinkets; they're 
very overpriced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pompeii" src="/articles/2023/res/pompeii_bath.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pompeii. I guess people... bathed here?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking through the ruins reminded me of Ozymandias: Here stood a nation, once 
the ruler of most of Europe, and all that remains around are ruins. Ruins that
were buried as a consequence of the wrath of nature, not even ruins that fell
into ruin via conquest. Sure, I guess people bathed here and slept there 2000 
years ago, but there was no sense of grandeur looking at them. Or maybe I'm 
not an archaeology / history buff. There were very pretty flowers at a few spots
though, and there was a lovely courtyard garden in one of the uptown villas.
Roman homies had amazing cribs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="pano" src="/articles/2023/res/roman_crib.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;One of the cleaner panos, if you can ignore my finger&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Meta&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Pompeii, the plan was to hop down to Sorrento and take the bus that 
goes along the Amalfi coast, covering all the coastal towns. After getting on 
the train, Vedang said that if we got off at Meta, had lunch and then took 
the bus from Meta itself to Positano rather than going all the way to Sorrento,
we'd be good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we got off at Meta, and started looking for a place to eat. Google Maps led 
us to a supermarket, and we wanted to eat at a proper place. The only issue 
is that in a small sleepy hill-town, most of the places are not open for lunch.
Walking along, we came across a futsal-bar which had a bunch of kids inside,
probably celebrating someone's birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Us:&lt;/em&gt; Are you open for Lunch?&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Person:&lt;/em&gt; I don't think so&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;awkward silence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Person:&lt;/em&gt; Hold on I'll call the owner
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;more waiting in awkward silence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Grandpa:&lt;/em&gt; O come-a in! come-a in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were ushered in by Grandpa (who probably owned the place) and asked to make 
ourselves comfortable. He informed us that they only had pasta for lunch, as the 
oven was off. Soon, Granddaughter (I assume) came to take our orders, and we 
ordered two pastas. We were given some bread and breadsticks to start, and soon 
the drinks (two coca-colas) arrived too, so we weren't left hungry for long.
They even offered to let us take the bread on the way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What followed though was the best pasta I've eaten in my life. Undoubtedly.
Perfectly cooked and perfectly seasoned. In the middle of a small town, when
they're supposed to be closed, they invited us in and served lunch. I come from
a land that believes in &lt;em&gt;Athithi Devo Bhava&lt;/em&gt;, but even our restaurants wouldn't
go this far. Truly amazing, and if you do visit Meta ever, check out 
&lt;a href="https://www.coventgardenpub.net/"&gt;Covent Garden Pub&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sorrento&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After paying for the meal and taking the train down to Sorrento, we finally 
arrived around 2 PM. We then had two options: visit Bagni Regina Giovanna 
(The secret bathing place of Queen Joanna I of Naples, basically a natural
cove) which would take up to three hours, or we wait an hour for the bus that
takes us to Positano. The bus that would take us up to Regina Giovanna would
also take 45 minutes, so we decided to walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so we set off uphill. The views were breathtaking and many a photo was taken,
but after walking uphill for 1.5 km, we were drenched in sweat. The walk after 
that point went something like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vedang:&lt;/em&gt; 👍&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me:&lt;/em&gt; 🚶&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Vedang:&lt;/em&gt; 👍👍&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me:&lt;/em&gt; 🚶&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Vedang:&lt;/em&gt; 👍👍👍&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me:&lt;/em&gt; What are you doing&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Vedang:&lt;/em&gt; Asking for a lift&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me:&lt;/em&gt; lmao do you think someone will give us a lift here? It's all tourist
buses and cars&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Vedang:&lt;/em&gt; Yeah if I get one you can walk &lt;em&gt;chuckles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;chuckles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Us:&lt;/em&gt; 🚶🚶&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A car pulls up&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Stranger:&lt;/em&gt; Do you want a lift?&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Us:&lt;/em&gt; :o :o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short: Someone gave us a lift to Bagni Regina Giovanna. Goodwill,
unlike lightning, struck the same spot twice in the span of 24 hours. I have no
words to describe what happened after. A twisting series of steps led to a
beach which truly took my breath away. I'll let the pictures do the talking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rg1" src="/articles/2023/res/regina_giovanna_adjacent.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rg2" src="/articles/2023/res/regina_giovanna_cove.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rg3" src="/articles/2023/res/regina_giovanna_outside.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Positano&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Positano bites deep. It is a dream place that isn't quite real when you are 
there and becomes beckoningly real after you have gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;~ John Steinbeck&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting out of Bagni Regina Giovanna at around 4, we had two options: 
Go to Positano, or go back to Naples. Going to Positano was what we wanted 
to do, but the bus and train schedules were not in our favour. Dejected, we 
went to a shop near the beach and got some energy drinks to rehydrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until a bus dropped by, and we hurriedly rushed on to it. The bus took us back 
down to the station, and we had reached just in time to make the bus to 
Positano. The only issue was that there were 5 buses all around. Walking around
and asking the bus drivers which one went to Positano, one of them said 
'This one'. We hurriedly hopped on, and this dream place suddenly became all 
too real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="positano_towns" src="/articles/2023/res/positano_towns.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no roads in Positano. It is a mishmash of small buildings tied 
together by steps, cobbled paths and the millions of dollars of the super-rich 
who come to vacation here. We did see a superyacht or two around the bay, and 
a huge number of people. Very few backpackers. It seems like the vacation spot 
of choice for those who own a private yacht, or those who are in their 
mid-thirties and are going on a moderately affluent vacation. Places to live 
are quite expensive, as is food. In spite of the prices, the beach here is as 
crowded as it gets. Surprising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scarcity and remoteness does ensure one thing: The water in Positano is
clear blue. Clear, like freshly-made crystal glass. I would provide a hex code
being a programmer, but no hex code can come close to expressing how blue the
water really is. It's something you'd have to see for yourself. Hopefully some
of these pictures capture it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rg2" src="/articles/2023/res/positano_water.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After frolicking on the beach, we had to get back. Taking the bus would mean 
that we would have to wait for thirty minutes, and also climb all the way back 
up the hill. Instead, we took the ferry. And that completes the gauntlet of 
&lt;strike&gt;infinity stones&lt;/strike&gt; means of travel, all in the span of a week: 
car, bus, train, boat, plane. The ferry ride was well worth it, even though we 
reached Sorrento by around 7:30 PM and had to take the train that was a bit 
late. The seas were as blue as the water on the beach, and with the wind 
running through your hair and the sun shining on your face, there is little else
that can make you as relaxed and happy as a ferry ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="positano" src="/articles/2023/res/positano.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rg3" src="/articles/2023/res/positano_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Roma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Rome" src="/articles/2023/res/rome.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sistine Chapel, as seen from Castel Sant'Angelo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day was to be spent in Rome, with plans of seeing the Vatican and 
other things nearby. We travelled down to Rome quite early with one of the
Italo high-speed trains, zipping through the Roman countryside at 300 km/h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="countryside" src="/articles/2023/res/countryside.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Roman countryside&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing we did was have breakfast at Roma Termini, and regroup with a 
friend who was at Rome. We then took the metro down to Vatican. After
bargaining with a tour guide for only skip-the-queue entry tickets to the
museum and sistine chapel (the ones on the website were all sold out), we
finally got some for a decent price with a student discount. The tickets were
for 1:30, and we had to regroup at their office for entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, St. Peter's square was a short hop away. It's much bigger than what
&lt;em&gt;Angels and Demons&lt;/em&gt; would lead you to believe, and it took a long time to 
circumnavigate the entire square. The catacombs are adjacent to the square and 
after asking two very serious swiss guards about them, we were told it was 
invite-only. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after making some more plans, we hopped out of the Vatican, and decided to 
walk down to Castel Sant'Angelo. There was a Gelato store near the Vatican, and
for €3 we got the most gigantic two scoops of Gelato I've ever had. It was so
comically big that the cone almost disappeared under it, and I had to
constantly lick the edges to keep the melting Gelato from dripping down.
Mmmmmmmm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Castel Sant'Angelo was a proper Renaissance castle, originally made as a tomb 
for Emperor Hadrian. Also made famous by Angels and Demons, and the path to 
Illumination. The castle itself was okay, but the real takeaways were the memories
we made with our friends roaming the place :) It had an observation deck from
where you could see most of Rome, and also get very good views of the Sistine
Chapel (see the title picture)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Castel Sant'Angelo, we went for Lunch. I don't know if we ate in the 
Vatican or in Rome, but we were stuck with a huge tax overhead and a very large
bill, so we probably ate in the Vatican. Also, word of advice from a friend: an
&lt;em&gt;Aperol Spritz&lt;/em&gt; sucks. It looks and tastes like cough syrup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT&lt;/strong&gt;: There are no restaurants in the Vatican, so we did eat in Rome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="sistine chapel" src="/articles/2023/res/sistine_chapel_streets.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have many pictures of the inside of the Vatican Museum, but what I saw
truly moved me. Every single surface was either gilded, marbled or intricately
painted. Marble statues from thousands of years ago were strewn across the entire
museum like pots and plates in a kitchen. It was not the detail in the art there 
that took my breath away (It was the most detailed, intricate art I've seen), 
but rather the sheer magnitude of art. Room after room, Chamber after Chamber 
filled with priceless artifacts and wall-to-wall frescoes and paintings. It is 
said that the Holy See was the most powerful entity in the middle ages, and 
I wouldn't doubt it. No wonder the western world fought crusades for Jerusalem
and conquered more than half of the planet. If the sheer opulence and the
magnitude of wealth here wouldn't convince Christians that their religion is
better than others, it would definetly convince a heathen that the Christian
god is wealthier than their god. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="milvian bridge" src="/articles/2023/res/milvian_bridge.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Battle of the Milvian Bridge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ceiling" src="/articles/2023/res/ceiling.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;If you told me this was Gold, I'd believe you&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I doubt the tacky paragraph and pictures above capture the essence of the
Vatican. It's something that has to be seen to be believed. Each of the
ceilings would have taken atleast a thousand man-hours to construct, and after
a point my neck would hurt from continuously staring up. There was so much
sensory overload that even the extraordinary became commonplace. So much that I
stopped taking pictures after the first few frescoes, and just shuffled through
the halls, agape at the scenes surrounding me. Versailles looked like a summer
fair in comparision to the Vatican Museum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, after going through the myriad chambers and ensemble of museums, we
made it to the Sistine Chapel. No photography was allowed, but everyone knows
what The Agony and The Ecstasy looks like. My only misconception was that I 
thought it would fill up the entire ceiling. Not so. It was this tiny painting
right in the centre amidst this huge ceiling filled with other paintings, so 
it was a bit underwhelming to see. Religious significance aside, The chapel
felt a bit overhyped to me, mostly because of the poor lighting and the huge
throng inside. I think some of the museums were more ornate and more intricate 
than the Chapel, but I may be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this whirlwind experience, we were back where we started. There wasn't 
enough time to visit another place, so we decided to take a bus to a park 
that was near Termini. We ambled in the park for around half an hour, wondering
about where life was to take us after the internship and what awaited us when 
we returned back to College for our final year. The time passed quicker than I 
wanted it to, and in the blink of an eye, we were seated in the train back to
Napoli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Warm weather, warmer people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like that, the vacation was over, and we had our flight scheduled to
Netherlands the following day. The stay was quite comfortable: our BnB had an 
amazing shower, was very well-stocked with neccessities and nothing really felt
lacking. It's the spark of life that sets Italy apart: people care. Even if
they don't, people exist. The occasional broken turnstile was replaced by a
Guard, the checkout at the cornerstore was operated by a Granny, the shops are
run by people who see tourists daily and speak English, and an attendant would
help you if you couldn't book tickets at the kiosk. There is just enough chaos
to make life interesting, but not uncomfortable. Again, I've not stayed there
at length so this may be the idealistic tourist in me speaking, but I would if
given the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we had an early flight, we packed up, left the keys to the room on the 
table and went out to the airport. Only to be greeted with a &lt;a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/environment/storm-disrupts-air-train-traffic-netherlands-2023-07-05/"&gt;red alert warning for the Netherlands&lt;/a&gt;
because of Storm Poly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to dock points from Napoli Airport here: our flight timings came and 
went, without any information about what was happening to our flight. The flight
crew came to the gate, and then were told that the flight was delayed. Resigned
to the fate of nature, they sat some distance from us and ordered their lunch.
It was both hilarious and sad to see. Fortunately, looking at the Schiphol app,
all the AirFrance-KLM flights were postponed to after 5 PM, and all other flights 
(including EasyJet and other budget carries) were cancelled. Guess which airplane
a backpacking college student was flying on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KLM. Not EasyJet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank god. I bought the expensive ticket on the advice of Vedang (after his 
EasyJet out of Geneva was cancelled), and I have never been happier to buy a
more expensive ticket than I was once we touched down at Schiphol safe and
sound, as my flight back to India was scheduled just the following day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All was still not well, as we were made to stand in queues for multiple hours 
and once we boarded the flight, we sat on the runway for a good forty-five 
minutes before going airborne. Missed out on a proper lunch, and had to make do 
with the snacks onboard the flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Last Supper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After landing in the Netherlands and hauling my luggage down to the room (which 
was tiny), my roomie went to Centraal. I had decided that I'd stuff myself full
after the long morning and skipping lunch. There weren't many good options to
eat living near the airport, but there was a Correndon hotel down the road from
where I put up near Schiphol, with very decent reviews on Google, and a quoted
price of €10-€20. I decided to walk down in my jeans and black hoodie. This
place had a 747 before the entrance, and after giving it a good look I swaggered
through the revolving doors, super hungry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me:&lt;/em&gt; Hi, I'd like a table for one&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Desk:&lt;/em&gt; Sure, would you like me to bill it to your room&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me, living in the Ibis down the road:&lt;/em&gt; No, I'd pay by card&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Desk:&lt;/em&gt; Okay, that would come to €33.98&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me, in my mind:&lt;/em&gt; OMGWTFML can't back down now&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Gulps&lt;/em&gt; Sure, here you go&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like that, I spent &amp;gt;60% of what I spent to live for a night here, on
food. Surrounded by all these old, fancy business execs whose companies were
paying for their food and lodging, and me in my hoodie and jeans :P You're only
young and dumb once, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hey, atleast the food was good. And it was an all-you-can-eat. I'd like to 
say no regrets, but that was the most money I've ever spent for a single meal
on myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="correndon chocolate fountain" src="/articles/2023/res/correndon.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chicken Curry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My flight back was uneventful, but the drive from Mumbai to Pune in the lashing
rain at 3 AM in the night was something to remember. The comforts of home are
so numerous so as to be unenumerable, and I enjoyed the two and a half weeks at
home doing absolutely nothing but waking up late and having good food. Oh, and
trekking to Visapur fort with my friends!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's been it. I know this is not the latest edition of Conde Nast Traveller,
so I'll refrain from writing a cheesy editor's note, but I'm quite pleased with
how this article turned out. This is one of, if not the biggest article I've 
written (6000+ words!). After reconsidering fleshing out the different sections multiple
times, I'm glad I took the effort to finally do so. However, this will be my 
first and last travelogue, because it takes a disproportionate amount of effort
to both recollect and document every single minutiae of your trip
&lt;a href="https://www.team-bhp.com/forum/travelogues/87398-yetiblog-weddings-drivings-france-germany-italy-croatia-slovenia-2.html"&gt;Sam Kapasi style&lt;/a&gt;,
and I don't want to do this while on the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Touring the world while young is a good way to break your assumptions, curb
your impulsivity and increase your tolerance. And travelling doesn't imply
zipping around town in an air-conditioned bus, stopping at only the tourist
attractions. Travelling implies using the public transport, drinking water from
the public fountains and finding your own path amongst the crowds thronging the
streets. If you do this, you'll soon realize that the world around is not as
everyone's Instagram stories tell you: there's a lot more to it than pretty
lights and beautiful sights. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bon Voyage!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous article is private for good reasons: I'm not
allowed to speak much about my work during the internship due to various IP
clauses, but if you want a general vibe, or want to know about the kind of 
work we did, you can check out &lt;a href="https://optiver.com/working-at-optiver/career-hub/chinmays-journey-as-a-tech-intern/"&gt;Chinmay's Official Interview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you really want to give the previous article a read, please reach out to me.
No guarantees on providing access though!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup id='footnote-1'&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Because I'm a Luddite from the 90's who doesn't 
post his whereabouts 24/7 on Instagram&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup id='footnote-2'&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; We did some other things as well, but I'll omit
them for now. Those who know, know ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup id='footnote-3'&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; Apparently she divorced them (it?) and is now
&lt;a href="https://www.snopes.com/news/2023/07/15/woman-married-eiffel-tower/"&gt;happily married to a fence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup id='footnote-4'&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; And if they spoke English.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="Intern"></category></entry><entry><title>Daft Punk and Interstella 5555</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/daft-punk-interstella.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-12-11T12:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-12-11T12:30:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2022-12-11:/articles/2022/daft-punk-interstella.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2001, Daft Punk were nowhere near the mask-rocking superstars they are today. 
The only album they had to their credit was their debut, &lt;em&gt;Homework&lt;/em&gt;, and their 
robot masks hadn't even materialized yet. In 2001, they came out with &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt;,
Which in many ways has defined their music style and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2001, Daft Punk were nowhere near the mask-rocking superstars they are today. 
The only album they had to their credit was their debut, &lt;em&gt;Homework&lt;/em&gt;, and their 
robot masks hadn't even materialized yet. In 2001, they came out with &lt;em&gt;Discovery&lt;/em&gt;,
Which in many ways has defined their music style and approach for the 21st 
century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of Discovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daft Punk didn't have their helmets before discovery. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let that sink in. Their most iconic feature came about as a story they wove, 
that there was "An Accident in the Studio", and since then, the helmets 
themselves have become more iconic than Thomas and Guy. If they choose, they 
could let the legend live on by handing down the helmets to someone else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we deviate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sounds in Discovery are very wide ranging: from the lyrical &lt;a href="https://music.youtube.com/watch?v=TZhxu5iCDnI&amp;amp;feature=share"&gt;Too Long&lt;/a&gt; to the
deep &lt;a href="https://music.youtube.com/watch?v=POSwzCFwUZ0&amp;amp;feature=share"&gt;Veridis Quo&lt;/a&gt;. 
There's a lot of variety, and while most would just listen to One More Time and 
Harder, Better, Faster, Stronger and think they're representative of the kind 
of work Daft Punk does (electronic disco pop with vocoder-ed vocals), that's 
far from the truth, and every song in this album has a story to tell. The story
of a band that's morphing into what they will be for the next two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interstella 5555&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if every song has a story to tell, how do we tell it? Daft Punk initially
planned to release every record on Discovery as a single, with an accompanying
music video. If you've seen the MV's for &lt;em&gt;One More Time&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Harder, Better,
Faster, Stronger&lt;/em&gt;, great. If not, let me refresh your memory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gAjR4_CbPpQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/FGBhQbmPwH8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you would've felt an overarching theme there. What ties these (and a couple other 
MV's) together? In a Pink Floyd-esque move, rather than releasing individual
MV's, Daft Punk decided to chain together all the songs in Discovery together
to make a complete musical. If that wasn't enough to get you excited, they tied
up with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leiji_Matsumoto"&gt;Leiji Matsumoto&lt;/a&gt; to
make it animated rather than live-action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3Qxe-QOp_-s" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was amazing to see as a daft punk fan: The entire story is beautiful, and 
is about an alien band that's abducted, shipped off to Earth and made to play 
corporate pop for profiting a major record label. The story is about how they 
escape this. What's even more interesting is that none of the characters ever 
speak: it's all just animation and lyrics. Letting the music speak for the
characters is amazing, and while it's easy on the ears and eyes of the viewers, 
I can only imagine how hard it must have been as an artist to create such 
coherence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Deeper Dive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've just watched this once: more trivia always pops up when I see something 
multiple times, but what's immediately noticeable is &lt;a href="https://www.vulture.com/2018/04/how-2001-a-space-odyssey-has-influenced-pop-culture.html"&gt;The 2001 effect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="anime" src="res/space_odyssey_1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="odyssey" src="res/space-odyssey-red.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="anime" src="res/space_odyssey_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="odyssey" src="res/space_odyssey_light_tunnel.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another bit of trivia: even though Daft Punk makes a cameo in the awards scene 
(Of course they do, they're &lt;em&gt;Daft Punk&lt;/em&gt;!), This scene is filled with tributes 
to people whose music Daft Punk have sampled for Discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Daft Punk cameo" src="res/daft_punk.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's Sister Sledge. &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7qyL2yN88pI"&gt;IL Macquilage Lady&lt;/a&gt; was sampled for &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L93-7vRfxNs"&gt;Aerodynamic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="sister sledge" src="res/sister_sledge.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is Eddie Johns (?), from whom &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JYya05epoZ8&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;More Spell on You&lt;/a&gt; was sampled for One More Time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="eddie johns" src="res/eddie_johns.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the Spice Girls?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="spice girls" src="res/spice_girls.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty sure this one is Mozart? (This comes later in the movie)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="mozart" src="res/mozart.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is Bob Marley?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="marley" src="res/bob_marley.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is Robert Plant?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="rob plant" src="res/robert_plant.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have zero clue who these two are, although they should be famous. Let me know 
in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="no idea" src="res/no_idea_1.png"&gt;
&lt;img alt="no idea" src="res/no_idea_2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pure visual treat if you're into Daft Punk, and it was an amazing 
experience delving into their discography. Some of the songs they sampled are 
amazing in themselves, and I'll be listening to them more, as well as giving 
this another view and updating whatever I find :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: You can find a list of the sample history of Discovery &lt;a href="https://www.whosampled.com/album/Daft-Punk/Discovery/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="General"></category></entry><entry><title>The Man Who Sold The World</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/man-who-sold-the-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-25T21:05:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-11-25T21:05:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2022-11-25:/articles/2022/man-who-sold-the-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We passed upon the stair&lt;br&gt;
We spoke of was and when&lt;br&gt;
Although I wasn't there&lt;br&gt;
He said I was his friend&lt;br&gt;
Which came as a surprise&lt;br&gt;
I spoke into his eyes&lt;br&gt;
"I thought you died alone,&lt;br&gt;
A long long time ago"&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh no, not me&lt;br&gt;
I never lost control&lt;br&gt;
You're …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We passed upon the stair&lt;br&gt;
We spoke of was and when&lt;br&gt;
Although I wasn't there&lt;br&gt;
He said I was his friend&lt;br&gt;
Which came as a surprise&lt;br&gt;
I spoke into his eyes&lt;br&gt;
"I thought you died alone,&lt;br&gt;
A long long time ago"&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh no, not me&lt;br&gt;
I never lost control&lt;br&gt;
You're face to face&lt;br&gt;
With the man who sold the world"&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I laughed and shook his hand&lt;br&gt;
And made my way back home&lt;br&gt;
I searched for form and land&lt;br&gt;
For years and years I roamed&lt;br&gt;
I gazed a gazeless stare&lt;br&gt;
At all the millions here&lt;br&gt;
I must have died alone&lt;br&gt;
A long, long time ago&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knows? Not me&lt;br&gt;
We never lost control&lt;br&gt;
You're face to face&lt;br&gt;
With the man who sold the world&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to write a story based on this, but the lyrics are so poetic. I don't 
want to detract from the mystery and intrigue of them one bit by fleshing my 
story out. Simply beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/SmTy_bweehQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Nirvana MTV unplugged cover of this song&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/fregObNcHC8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="General"></category></entry><entry><title>Cold Showers, Adulting and More</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/cold-showers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-11-22T09:45:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-11-22T09:45:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2022-11-22:/articles/2022/cold-showers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Day 249 of taking a cold shower. It's something I've been doing since April, 
and although the temperature has fallen and the geyser in my bathroom has been
fixed come winter, it's a habit I want to keep. Nothing makes you feel as alive
as a cold shower does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Day 249 of taking a cold shower. It's something I've been doing since April, 
and although the temperature has fallen and the geyser in my bathroom has been
fixed come winter, it's a habit I want to keep. Nothing makes you feel as alive
as a cold shower does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of durations, it's also been exactly a month since my last post. A lot 
has happened since, and I've been too wrapped up in the happenings to get time 
to post here once a week. This sem has been no different than others, with you 
progressively realizing the depth to which you've sunk in the quicksand only as
more classes happen and the majors draw near.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think I've gotten the hang of this. Not just the semester, but life in 
general, and rather than looking at what I can do here, I'm looking outward to 
upcoming goals in life. Ah, too much abstraction. TL;DR: With the endsems 
ending tomorrow, I expect to write more frequently here ;)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="General"></category></entry><entry><title>Intern Inferno</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/intern-inferno.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-14T15:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-08-14T15:30:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2022-08-14:/articles/2022/intern-inferno.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everything goes exactly as planned. That's why it's a plan, not a certainty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aiming in&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this entire &lt;em&gt;joomla&lt;/em&gt; started, I asked myself: &lt;em&gt;What is it I want from an intern&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to tour: I didn't pick up a foreign research intern this summer, and was tired of …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everything goes exactly as planned. That's why it's a plan, not a certainty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aiming in&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this entire &lt;em&gt;joomla&lt;/em&gt; started, I asked myself: &lt;em&gt;What is it I want from an intern&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to tour: I didn't pick up a foreign research intern this summer, and was tired of hearing/seeing how others were roaming the world while I was &lt;a href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/badminton-habits.html"&gt;scooping shuttles off the floor of my room&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted something that paid well: Apart from the feel-good factor, a good paying intern would put money for my masters' in the bank&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above both of these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted something that would &lt;strong&gt;help me in the future&lt;/strong&gt;: Research or core CS/Math roles would provide both relevant work experience and also appeal to universities when I go for my Masters. I definetly didn't want to pick up finance/consulting/&lt;em&gt;enterprise/backend/frontend&lt;/em&gt; development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted something &lt;strong&gt;fun&lt;/strong&gt;: Writing high-stakes trading algorithms, making hyper-efficient and superfast systems on embedded devices, implementing object recognition on embedded sensors, receiving patents/publishing papers on new models and algorithms is a small but representative subset of the kind of work I wanted to do this summer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way of looking at this is &lt;strong&gt;saying no&lt;/strong&gt;: proceed by elimination rather than addition. This requires knowing yourself very well, and seeing if a role really resonates with what you want to do. Eg if you're a product person and have worked in programming clubs, developing systems, then a SDE role would appeal to you. Don't apply to anything other than SDE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, I built up a small shortlist of companies to apply to. Mostly quant and research roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bluffington, but with higher stakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intern season this time formally started off in early July, when talks were held by the Office of Career Services and the resumé portal opened for a short while (albeit there were several deadline extensions). For context, your OCS CV is what companies would shortlist you based on, and for everything you wrote on there, proof was required. I didn't have much to put on it except a large number of projects, some acad achievements and some volunteer experience, and I believe that's more than enough for a Tech CV (where shortlisting is mostly done either through CG or through your performance in some arcane test that the company conjures). Just be completely aware of what you're putting in there, and what each project was: the CV is used for HR/Face to face interviews, and you'll probably be quizzed on atleast a couple domains where you've done projects. And please, please, &lt;em&gt;don't bluff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: this is only relevant to tech/research roles. I have no idea what makes a good finance/consult CV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Dance of Dragons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies started with their Pre-Placement Talks from the 19th (?): Higher paying ones went first, and it was a mixed bag. Some were lackluster, and some were brilliant. Soon after which, applications opened up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the most important thing here is to &lt;strong&gt;Stick to your list&lt;/strong&gt;: You'll see friends and most people applying to absolutely everything and anything in the hopes that an intern will materialize somewhere. There are multiple downsides to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too many tests will tire you out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if you clear all the tests and are shortlisted for interviews from multiple companies, there are only so many Day 1 slots that OCS will allocate to you (I think 4 is the upper limit), so even if you want to, you can't sit everywhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, this does require a lot of tenacity and self-belief, and a good CG/plenty of skill as well. There's no one right answer, just make sure you don't switch your strategy out of desperation midway (eg go through your list, then realize that if there are too many companies open and your chances are low, apply to all of them, or vice versa). Go in with a plan, and try to stick to it as much as possible from your end, because you can't control what happens outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Longlists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After applications, shortlists for tests begin to arrive. Companies have free will in how they'll shortlist people: some are very transparent, and some are opaque to the point of being devious. The test processes for some of the most wanted companies spans multiple tests rather than just one, so keep an eye out on that as well. Also, while OCS will do their best to avoid test slot clashes, you will become a walking zombie if you take too many or, in the worst case, will have a bunch of slot clashes. Combined with 8am offline classes and 11pm tests, &lt;em&gt;just don't push yourself by applying to as many companies as you can&lt;/em&gt;. Just don't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect is to not be disappointed if you don't make a test shortlist: it's probably just a random thing (unless there are clear patterns such as a CG cutoff), and you shouldn't beat yourself up about it. Learning to not let these things affect you is hard, but an important learning nevertheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tests and shortlists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, the tests. Probably my least favourite part, because unless you're super amazing at the test, there's a complete black box behind the outcome (how well your test went) and the interview shortlist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A test I gave where I thought I'd done pretty well (there was a monte carlo approximation problem that I did nicely), didn't result in a shortlist. Others (who didn't do this problem) got shortlisted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A test where I thought I'd done poorly resulted in me getting a shortlist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A test where I'd done decent made no difference, because company in question just shortlisted CS DR 1-7, and two people who'd blasted their test to shreds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A company which gave a test to a majority of their shortlist and an interview to a minority, had a significant % acceptance difference between the two methods of testing. Clearly, one was better than the other. Sadly I pulled the short straw here, and didn't make it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A company which had multiple rounds of tests, and finally a pre-interview, completely roasted me in the pre-interview, while several others said that they'd found their pre-interview to be &lt;em&gt;very chill&lt;/em&gt;. They got shortlisted, while I didn't.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, most companies won't have tests that are relevant to the work you'd be doing at the company. It's mostly a bunch of CP questions (gets harder for more valuable companies), and if you're in quant, some math MCQ's. Very few companies invest a lot of time and effort in the kind of questions they ask/the processes they take, and it's a pleasure in some sense to give those tests. Also, if the test is too easy, there is no differentiator between you and someone &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably where the completely stochastic nature of life comes face-to-face with you: The stochasticity of the outcome is inversely proportional to your skill, and the only way to minimize it is to be an order-of-magnitude better than everyone else. Or, just get lucky. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has two important implications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you got rejected, it doesn't mean that you're worse than the others who got shortlisted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you got shortlisted, it doesn't mean that you're better than the others who got rejected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very skilled (and very humble) friend keeps saying &lt;em&gt;Tukke pe jee raha hu mai&lt;/em&gt; (I'm living on a fluke) whenever praised for his skills, and it's a brilliant thing to do: accept the universe is larger than you and be grateful for it's outcomes. That way, you're always humble and happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preference Filling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all things, have no preferences. 
~ Miyamoto Musashi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should be a no-brainer by this point. However, more context: Quant got into a bidding war over Talent, with multiple raises: I don't want to quote exact numbers here, but there was an almost 50% increase in the stipend offered, and they were already offering a lot. In addition, Quant companies with foreign bases leveraged their position to offer foreign roles as well, paid in GBP/SGD, which would be a no-brainer for most&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Unfortunately, when I started, this was not there and some of these companies didn't make my shortlist, but for others, if the goalposts change and if you had them in your shortlist, now would be a good time to realistically reconsider where you want to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another note about Day 1 and Day 2: The placement system here works to ensure that the maximum number of people get an intern the quickest. As a result, internships are spread across two days, and if you get an offer on Day 1, you're out of contention in Day 2. Most core/research companies come in on Day 2 (Day 1 is quant/finance/consult/SDE mostly, because they pay the most), and if your heart is set on core/research, it's safest to skip Day 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, keeping in line the above quote, if you do get shortlisted for a Day 1 company which is worse than a Day 2 company, it's sad, but there's not much you can do. Just remember to have fun when you go for the intern!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Faceoff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you're walking in for interviews, sharply dressed, with your resume/CV in hand. What now? It's easy to say "Just be cool", but very hard to do. I think the most important thing is to go with the flow and be yourself, atleast in tech. And remember to keep it simple: start off with the simplest solution you can think of, then layer in complexity. In an interview, emphasis is on communication and clarity of thought rather than complexity, and if you're starting off simple, it's much easier to hook in your interviewer and keep him in your thought process rather than starting off complex and trying to break down complexity to explain to him (mostly because they anyway have a more complex problem, which they'll spring upon you once you solve the simple problem correctly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So your interviews are over, and you're waiting at your hostel room, playing cards and biding time till your offer comes in. Several others have received on-the-spot offers, and you've been told by all your interviewers that you'll "get to know via your placement cell". Someone pings you asking if you got the offer, because XYZ got it now, and you run to your laptop and load the portal. What does your next LinkedIn post say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;drumrolls&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="res/spoiler.css"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class='spoiler'&gt;
&lt;div class='spoiler-prompt'&gt; I'm pleased to announce that I'll be joining ... &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='spoiler-text'&gt; I'm pleased to announce that I'll be joining &lt;a href="https://www.optiver.com"&gt;Optiver&lt;/a&gt; at their Amsterdam office next summer as a &lt;b&gt;Software Engineering Intern&lt;/b&gt;. I'll be working on optimizing their low-latency systems and finding out what goes into the tech that makes one of the world's leading market makers tick.
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/linkedin post&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truth be told, it's not as simple as this. Never is. Here's a small sankey diagram I made of how the entire process unfolded&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="res/intern_sankey.svg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had two shortlists and ended up converting both, and I really enjoyed the interview processes in both the companies I applied to. Very kind and very smart interviewers, very cool people overall. Would've loved to send one half of me to each company, but unfortunately that's not possible :')&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some resources I used for Quant Prep can be &lt;a href="https://github.com/Aniruddha-Deb/quant-prep"&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a lot that's not been talked about here: Diversity hiring, Waitlists, Walk-ins and Day 2 chaos. There are a few (several?) more nuances in placements, but with my experience here, one thing is pretty certain: &lt;strong&gt;I'm not sitting for placements&lt;/strong&gt;. It's a better investment of time and energy to work on a nice BTech Project, and focus on the near future &lt;!--rather than threading needles and shooting toothpicks at chances coming in via a draconian big-brotheresque middleman.--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best, and happy intern hunting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;That's not all they did. Some invited their shortlist to dinner, some handed out t-shirts to their shortlist, some sent out emails inviting their shortlist to WA groups where they can ask anything about the company, and so on and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="Programming"></category><category term="Probability"></category></entry><entry><title>Orbital Maneuvers and the Oberth Effect</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/orbital-oberth.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-07-05T15:30:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-07-05T15:30:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2022-07-05:/articles/2022/orbital-oberth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once a rocket is in orbit, if it needs to change it's orbit (either from a lower to a higher orbit, or from a circular to an elliptical orbit), it needs to execute an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orbital_maneuver"&gt;Orbital Maneuver&lt;/a&gt;. This is accomplished by using a small impulse from thrusters to change the tangential …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once a rocket is in orbit, if it needs to change it's orbit (either from a lower to a higher orbit, or from a circular to an elliptical orbit), it needs to execute an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orbital_maneuver"&gt;Orbital Maneuver&lt;/a&gt;. This is accomplished by using a small impulse from thrusters to change the tangential velocity, and hence slip into a different orbit as a consequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Types of Orbital Maneuvers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two types of orbital maneuvers: the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hohmann_transfer_orbit"&gt;Hohmann transfer orbit&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bi-elliptic_transfer"&gt;Bi-elliptic transfer&lt;/a&gt;. The Hohmann transfer is faster, but the bi-elliptic one can use less fuel in some cases&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/df/Hohmann_transfer_orbit.svg" width='300px' height='360px'/&gt;
&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/83/Bi-elliptic_transfer.svg" width='477px' height='360px'&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;figures showing a) Hohmann transfer and b) Bi-elliptic transfer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Oberth Effect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberth_effect"&gt;Oberth Effect&lt;/a&gt; is interesting: roughly what it states is that &lt;strong&gt;A rocket will gain more velocity while firing it's engines at a higher velocity than by firing them at a lower velocity&lt;/strong&gt;. This is because the fuel has kinetic energy by virtue of the rocket's motion, and travelling at higher velocity = more kinetic energy in the fuel that the engines convert to exhaust gases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This effect can be used in a gravitational slingshot, when at the periapsis (closest point) of an elliptical orbit, a burn is more effective and gives you higher velocity gain as compared to burning as you're entering the gravitational well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that this is only applicable to reaction engines: it's less effective for something such as an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ion_thruster"&gt;Ion Engine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Philosophical Connotations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My father is an aerospace engineer by training, and this popped up in one of our long conversations about life (I've recently returned home, so enjoying these moments). In somewhat of a continuation to the &lt;a href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2021/this-summer.html"&gt;World is a Universe, and Life is your Trajectory&lt;/a&gt; idea, this rocket took off when I got into IIT Delhi, and the second (third?) stage burn gave me my Department Change. I'm peacefully in one orbit now, but over the next two years, I'd have to prepare for the next orbit change: my internship, followed by applications for Masters and/or Placements. As a result, a majority of my efforts would lie in timing and firing the burn required for this orbital maneuver, rather than finding the path of least resistance in my current orbit (which I believe I've already done in the past year).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying healthy, focused, and motivated would be the primary goal for the next two years, while slowly detatching from other college-centric and people-focused activities and focusing more on the future and my skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: a lot of new articles have a more personal flavour to them, courtesy me having my professional and this webpage separate, and also as a consequence of being inspired by &lt;a href="https://basil08.github.io/post/"&gt;a friend's blog&lt;/a&gt;. Let's see how long I stick with it :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry><entry><title>Leadership, among many other things</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/leadership.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-06-26T23:15:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-06-26T23:15:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2022-06-26:/articles/2022/leadership.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gazettale, BSP's premier interhostel competition, for which our team worked day and night, recently released the final standings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we're fifth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pop the champagne and dance, team, for we're fifth!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="udai_fifth" src="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/res/udai_fifth.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jokes aside, I'm lukewarm about the result. Proud of what a ragtag bunch of people came together and assembled in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gazettale, BSP's premier interhostel competition, for which our team worked day and night, recently released the final standings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we're fifth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pop the champagne and dance, team, for we're fifth!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="udai_fifth" src="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/res/udai_fifth.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jokes aside, I'm lukewarm about the result. Proud of what a ragtag bunch of people came together and assembled in the span of around two weeks, but simultaneously disappointed for not reaching the lofty expectations we set of ourselves. Hindsight is 20/20 and often very saddening, for there is seldom joy in finding out what you couldn't see earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, let's see what hindsight has in store for us, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So What Happened?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Himadri had the incoming BSP GSec leading the team, along with two incoming chief editors and two incoming creative team members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aravali had three chief editors leading the team, along with a very talented senior in design. One of the chief editors, a very passionate writer, wrote 90% of the magazine content on his own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zanskar had the Web editor, along with an incumbent Creative team member and Chief Editor in their team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kumaon? I don't know what Kumaon pulled out of the bag, but the difference between them and us wasn't much (For reference, Zanskar dominated the content scores, while Aravali dominated the design section. Himadri was balanced across both, courtesy of picking a theme and sticking to it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then we have Udai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8 freshers and 4 second-years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who pulled our team to fifth place.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also came third in design, even though Rahul stormed into my room 4 days before the deadline and said "Video games". This is the part where I say "The Rest is History", but history is written by the victors, and we're not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What about Leadership?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treating this experience as a chance to exercise my leadership skills is probably the right way of looking at it. While I won't pat myself on the back (there were many things that I could've done better), I think more has to be said about the entire performance framework that teams operate upon. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with Culture. Yes, the buzzword that hostel reps throw around all the time to get participation. The reality of hostel culture is that similar to organizations, a few key, experienced seniors can accomplish much more and channelize much more effectively the lower, inexperienced team members' efforts. More so, these seniors are intimately involved with the club and have a say in what happens eg if deadlines need to be postponed. Having seniors in a hostel belonging to a club is vital to inculcate &lt;em&gt;culture&lt;/em&gt; for that club in that hostel. Seniors would need to evangelize and lead team efforts here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But Why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seniors aren't getting much out of it. If anything, Juniors and Seniors are on their way out of the institute and should focus on themselves, rather than their freshie and sophie counterparts who would be more enthusiastic about this. Unless they are in secretary/GSec positions where things would look good on their CV (and are playing the political Game of Thrones in IITD, a very taxing and time-consuming hobby for someone not looking at consulting), the only reason for them to invest the kind of effort that they're investing is purely altruistic: out of passion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's take the above cases: all the seniors in the winning hostel(s) either cared very deeply for their hostel and were passionate about the activity, or had some skin in the game (vested interests in obtaining a position in BSP for the upcoming term). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has a cascading effect: More skilled seniors = More skilled juniors, and more skilled juniors = a better result. Doesn't matter if you're &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Down_Periscope"&gt;Thomas Dodge&lt;/a&gt; or if anime has made you believe &lt;em&gt;the superpower of friendship&lt;/em&gt;, unless each of your team members can get 20 illustrations done in a day in illustrator, your magazine simply won't have enough design to fill it's pages. Unless your seniors churn out ideas rapidly and have a unifying vision that the team can rally behind, your magazine will read like a patchwork quilt. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The way forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking about leadership in a personal context is always a very dicey thing. I admit that in whatever capacity I led the team and in whatever role I played, I was suboptimal in some aspects and superoptimal in others. Maybe I didn't balance the scales properly. I'll admit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at a silver lining, we made two teams this time: which meant that more freshers were introduced to the entire process, and &lt;strike&gt;hopefully&lt;/strike&gt; definetly from next year onwards, we'll have a stronger footing in BSP, and on a more meta-level, inculcate better leaders.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry><entry><title>Freedom, Recaptured.</title><link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/freedom.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-05-30T17:10:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-05-30T17:10:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddhadeb.com,2022-05-30:/articles/2022/freedom.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the creation of my &lt;a href="https://www.cse.iitd.ac.in/~cs1200869"&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt; (safari butchers the CSS :/), I've now got more creative liberty and artistic freedom on the content I post here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first made this blog, it used to be my own little corner of the internet. That changed once more people got to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the creation of my &lt;a href="https://www.cse.iitd.ac.in/~cs1200869"&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt; (safari butchers the CSS :/), I've now got more creative liberty and artistic freedom on the content I post here. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first made this blog, it used to be my own little corner of the internet. That changed once more people got to know about it, and I subconsciously put more pressure on myself to keep a strong technical background to whatever I post. The problem with this approach is that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Articles take time! Writing theoretical deep dives often needs me to completely revisit whatever I studied, and they take upwards of a day or two to draft, edit, proofread and publish. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All work and no play makes Jack a dull boy! There's very little stuff here that's an easy read: all I mostly post are either 300-word math articles or 3000-word short stories now. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the older days, when I blogged on blogspot, I'd often get 0 views on a lot of articles. Zero! That was ok, as it felt like I blogged for myself and that whatever I said had minimal repercussions, but with this website, it feels a bit different. Self-imposed straitjacket, I'm aware, but hopefully the official website takes that pressure away now, and I can get back to posting more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's to more interesting reads this year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="General"></category><category term="General"></category></entry></feed>