<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Aniruddha Deb - Physics</title><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/feeds/physics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/</id><updated>2020-12-03T10:28:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>An introduction to Quantum Mechanics</title><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/articles/2020/quantum-intro.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-03T10:28:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-03T10:28:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddha-deb.github.io,2020-12-03:/articles/2020/quantum-intro.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn a subject is to try teaching it to others. Unfortunately,
I'm quite bad at teaching, and most of it will be incorrect anyways, so I'll
try to capture whatever I've learnt in Quantum Mechanics so far in this article. 
Note that I'm not an expert …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The best way to learn a subject is to try teaching it to others. Unfortunately,
I'm quite bad at teaching, and most of it will be incorrect anyways, so I'll
try to capture whatever I've learnt in Quantum Mechanics so far in this article. 
Note that I'm not an expert in Quantum Mechanics, and these notes are primarily
for my own understanding of the subject. Pointing out errors and suggesting 
improvements is appreciated :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Quantum Mechanics?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good question, which doesn't get enough attention. For most of us, 
we have to learn quantum mechanics because it's in the course curriculum, or 
because "classical mechanics fails at the microscopic level" or some BS like that.
&lt;a href="https://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/III_01.html"&gt;Chapter 1 of the Feynman Lectures, Vol. 3&lt;/a&gt; 
explains this amazingly, and if you're still not satisfied and want a more 
hardcore explanation, check out the afterword of &lt;a href="https://www.fisica.net/mecanica-quantica/Griffiths%20-%20Introduction%20to%20quantum%20mechanics.pdf"&gt;Griffiths' Introduction to 
Quantum Mechanics&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Quantum mechanics primarily arises to explain the behaviour of things 
that cannot be measured without disturbing their state. Like the electron or 
photon in a double slit experiment, trying to measure their position would 
cause a transfer of energy, however infinitesimal. This would disturb them from
the state that they were in, which would defeat the purpose of the measurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wave functions and Probabilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question that arises is how do we explain the behaviour of something
that we can't measure? We do this using something called a 'wave function'. The
wave function is called so, because it has a huge amount in common with the 
amplitude of a classical wave (see &lt;a href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/274988/what-is-the-etymology-of-the-term-wave-function"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more). 
Since we can't measure the actual location, all we can do is estimate the properties
of the particle using a set of probabilities. Suppose, we have a black box with 
a marble in it, divided into 4 quadrants. Something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="sorry shutterstock :P" src="res/box.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say that the marble can pass through the partitions; then, the probability
that the marble is in a particular quadrant at any given time is $1/4$. The wavefunction
for this system would then be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\psi(Q_x, Q_y) = \frac{1}{4}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where $Q_x$ and $Q_y$ represent the quadrant number along the x-axis and y-axis respectively.
The wavefunction being constant means that &lt;strong&gt;the probability of finding the 
particle in any quadrant is the same&lt;/strong&gt;. Some assumptions
are being made here: the marble is very small in comparision to the quadrant size 
(thus, it can't be in two quadrants at the same time), it's mass is finite and 
known and it can collide with the walls of the box without a loss of energy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, suppose we had to predict the location of the marble a bit more accurately: 
let's increase the number of partitions to 4 per axis, so that we now have 
16 slots. The probability distribution would probably change now; there's a 
higher probability of the marble being in the middle 4 regions as compared to the 
other regions. If we make an infinite number of partitions, then the wav&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Physics"></category><category term="Physics"></category><category term="Quantum Mechanics"></category></entry></feed>