<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Aniruddha Deb - Writing</title><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/feeds/writing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/</id><updated>2021-08-14T21:20:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Updates on Life in general</title><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/articles/2021/updates-on-life.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-14T21:20:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-08-14T21:20:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddha-deb.github.io,2021-08-14:/articles/2021/updates-on-life.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't done one of these in a year or so (&lt;a href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2020/iit-delhi-mnc.html#iit-delhi-mnc"&gt;this was the previous one&lt;/a&gt;), and neither have I written content exclusively for my blog for atleast a few months now, so it's a good time to do one of these because &lt;em&gt;a lot has changed in the past …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't done one of these in a year or so (&lt;a href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2020/iit-delhi-mnc.html#iit-delhi-mnc"&gt;this was the previous one&lt;/a&gt;), and neither have I written content exclusively for my blog for atleast a few months now, so it's a good time to do one of these because &lt;em&gt;a lot has changed in the past one year&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Let's start with summer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past two months have been amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn't even sum up just how great they've been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a lot of what I liked, some of what I didn't like, very little of what I hate, and everything made me a better individual. I realize that sounds straight out of the pages of a corporate brochure, but I promise it's the truth. Even though I stepped into summer without a concrete plan or project, I ended up accomplishing more than I expected, and even if you ignore all of that, I found some amazing things along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Now something concrete&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most concrete thing that pops out to me is my department change. Yes, everyone knew it was coming. Yes, &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; knew it was coming (so much so that I sat in the CS orientation rather than the MT orientation after the first semester), and Yes, I wasn't surprised when the official notification was finally sent out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as every day goes by, I come to terms a bit more with the magnitude of what truly happened. Just because you know something significant will happen, it doesn't take the edge off the magnitude of your achievement, when it finally happens. You find it hard to stand stoically and claim "&lt;span  style="font-size: 12pt;"&gt;अरे ये तो होना ही था&lt;/span&gt;", and everyday, I still ponder in amazement when I open my inbox and it reads &lt;code&gt;cs1200869&lt;/code&gt; rather than &lt;code&gt;mt6200869&lt;/code&gt;, thinking 'damn. This happened'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This couldn't have happened without everyone else who was involved, and unlike JEE, this time I didn't do it sitting alone in my room. I did it in the midst of my friends, my hostelmates and everyone else at IIT Delhi, and seeing the congratulatory messages pour in when the results finally came in was breathtaking. Thank you to everyone I've met at IITD so far; you guys and gals have been amazing, and when campus reopens, I can't wait to spend the rest of whatever little time we have with you: playing, talking or just aimlessly wandering through our campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thing that happened is the elections; I'll probably write on this a bit more later, but the good part is that I'm a Quizzing Club representative now, as well as a convenor in Debating Society! Quizzing and Debating are two activites I really enjoyed doing in my first year, and it feels great to finally be more involved in both of them now. Looking forward to hosting more quizzes and adjudicating or tabulating more debates, rather than merely participating in quizzes or debates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of academic things, I attended the IBM &lt;a href="https://qiskit.org/events/summer-school/"&gt;Qiskit Global Summer School in Quantum Computing&lt;/a&gt; for two weeks in July, which was also a great experience. We received a crash course in quantum computing and quantum machine learning, supplemented by five amazing labs, all of which I really enjoyed doing. I am also pleased to be a &lt;a href="https://scholarships.reliancefoundation.org/"&gt;Reliance Foundation Scholar in Artificial Intelligence and Computer Sciences&lt;/a&gt;, the onboarding event for which is scheduled on the 19th of August. Finally, it was great attending the events and camps organized by those at IITD: The Summer of Competitive Programming by ANCC and the Summer of Machine Learning by AIMLC. Both of them were great learning opportunities; the latter giving rise to &lt;a href="https://apps.aniruddhadeb.com/MathSolver"&gt;MathSolver&lt;/a&gt; (Article on that soon too, I promise).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The little things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There weren't many of these that I can remember now, but I designed the Quizzing Club Introductory poster this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="res/repteam_final_2.png" style="width: 100%; height: auto; max-width: 35vw;"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also applied for the Board of Student Publications, the press arm of IIT Delhi, and they had a very interesting google form that we needed to fill to be shortlisted for an interview. I will be uploading my responses to that form soon enough, but I filled that out in the first week of August, and it was a fun exercise filling that in, because I hadn't written anything original in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for Quizzing and Debating, I quizzed a lot and won nothing :P (best fresher, yes but that's a club award and not a quiz). the same goes for debating, except that I managed to break in my first external debate. The external debate was fun, albeit a bit exhausting. I need to get used to those :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did a bit of number theory and cryptography as well in the summers, learning what AES, RSA and all of those were. Some competitive programming was also on the list (&lt;a id="codeforces" href="" style="font-family: helvetica neue,Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif; font-weight: 700; font-size: 12pt"&gt;aniruddha_deb&lt;/a&gt; on CodeForces, &lt;a href="https://atcoder.jp/users/aniruddha_deb"&gt;aniruddha_deb&lt;/a&gt; on AtCoder), and I learnt a few more algorithms there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third semester is in full swing by now, and it's time to look beyond the horizon to further challenges. I'm enjoying all the computer courses so far, in spite of the several ominous warnings that seniors have given me, about CS being assignment hell (It's the first week, so I'll give them the benefit of doubt). Mathematics is also great (another article on some probability theory coming soon), and I'm trying to keep a healthy balance between everything else. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to talk a bit more about onboarding and internships; I meditated long and hard on these two topics, and finally came to the nihilistic conclusion that in the short term, &lt;em&gt;both of them don't matter&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding onboarding, seeing everyone meeting up and enjoying life simultaneously makes me happy and fills me with the fear of missing out. I'm not going to lie that it hurts at times to imagine myself in the pictures. However, that won't help at this stage. The conclusion I had reached with my parents was that it was too risky to onboard, and even though I had to see a lot of my friends go to campus, I've stood by that decision so far, and the workload of the new semester helps solidify that stand more. Nevertheless, doesn't matter now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding internships, first phase placements passed me by, and I was left wondering whether I made a mistake by not applying to them. Again, the result I reached on thinking a bit more was that second phase is always there, and if not that, I can always reach out and get internships on my own. Whatever decisions I took, I took them keeping in mind alternative actions, and it is pointless to question those decisions midway through their arc. Only after all the arrows have been shot and my quiver is empty, should I seriously question my decisions. Till then, sticking to them is my best bet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the larger perspective of things, both of these are inconsequential; I will inevitably be onboarded sooner or later, and I will inevitably get an internship, sooner or later. It's only the local minima that is preventing me from seeing the global maxima of the landscape of life, and this too shall pass. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Anything else?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the Qiskit summer school, I took a break from everything for a week or so. I was yearning for a holiday, and I hadn't had one in a long time, so I switched off WhatsApp for a week and connected with the world around me. This was a refreshing experience, and it was the only time in the summer vacations that I can honestly claim felt like a 'vacation'. Some might argue that's a bad thing, and I should relax more often; In my opinion, it was just right. All I did was sketch a bit, write some poetry, play some volleyball and sleep a lot, and life was good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anime! Yes, I watched a lot of anime. We had a clannad watchalong with friends, and I finished Steins;Gate on my own. What a show! I'm currently watching Code Geass, but that's proceeding at a snails' pace because &lt;strike&gt;I'm also watching the good doctor right now&lt;/strike&gt; there's a lot of academic workload now. I also tried my hand at the clannad visual novel, but that's very slow again, so I play that occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing was this &lt;a href="https://github.com/Aniruddha-Deb/strattech-intern-assignment"&gt;COVID vaccine analysis&lt;/a&gt; that I did, as part of the joining assignment for a small startup from our campus. Even though that didn't happen, I learnt a lot from this assignment, and I'll write about it a bit more sometime (this is a recurring trend; I promise more articles than I actually write :P)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;(here's a bonus for you)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CodeForces username badge uses a CF API request to change the color. This uses the CodeForces API to obtain the rank of the user, then adds that as a class, which the CSS then takes care of. Here's how it works:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;getCFLink&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;req&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;XMLHttpRequest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cfId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;codeforces&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;username&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cfId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;innerText&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// yes, I should urlencode the usernames, but it works for now&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cfId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;href&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;https://codeforces.com/profile/&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;addEventListener&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;load&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;reply&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;parse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;responseText&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;reply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;status&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;OK&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;rank&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;reply&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;rank&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;-&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nx"&gt;cfId&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;classList&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;add&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;rank&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;GET&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;https://codeforces.com/api/user.info?handles=&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nx"&gt;req&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;send&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The same cannot be done for AtCoder&lt;/em&gt;, because neither does AtCoder have an API nor does it allow cross-origin requests, so the AtCoder badge would have to remain plain for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading so far, and stay tuned for what's to follow :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="styles/cftitles.css"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;

    function getCFLink() {
        var oReq = new XMLHttpRequest();
        var cfId = document.getElementById("codeforces");
        var username = cfId.innerText;
        cfId.href = "https://codeforces.com/profile/" + username;
        oReq.addEventListener("load", () =&gt; {
            var reply = JSON.parse(oReq.responseText);
            if (reply.status === "OK") {
                var rank = reply.result[0].rank.replace(" ", "-");
                cfId.classList.add(rank);
            }
        });
        oReq.open("GET", "https://codeforces.com/api/user.info?handles="+username);
        oReq.send();
    }

    /* Does not work because AtCoder does not allow cross-origin requests, F
    function getAtcoderLink() {
        var req = new XMLHttpRequest();
        var atcId = document.getElementById('atcoder');
        var username = atcId.innerText;
        atcId.href = "https://atcoder.jp/users" + username;

        const parser = new DOMParser();

        req.addEventListener("load", () =&gt; {
            var doc = parser.parseFromString(req.responseText);
            var span = doc.getElementsByClassName('user-red user-orange user-yellow user-blue user-cyan user-green user-brown user-gray user-unrated user-admin');
            atcId.classList.add(span.classList[0]);
        });
        req.open("GET", "https://atcoder.jp/users/"+username);
        req.send();     
    }*/

    getCFLink();

&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Writing"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry><entry><title>How it Happened</title><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/articles/2021/how-it-happened.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-02T13:11:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-08-02T13:11:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddha-deb.github.io,2021-08-02:/articles/2021/how-it-happened.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;"Baba, I got Mathematics and Computing Dual at IITD", I told my father excitedly on the day the first round allocations were over. "It probably won't change now". Certain of this, I returned back to whatever I was doing, excitedly waiting for the seat allocations to get over (while simultaneously …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;"Baba, I got Mathematics and Computing Dual at IITD", I told my father excitedly on the day the first round allocations were over. "It probably won't change now". Certain of this, I returned back to whatever I was doing, excitedly waiting for the seat allocations to get over (while simultaneously crossing my fingers for the slightest hope of a branch upgrade, as we all do). Even though the campus was not opening and the semester was planned to be conducted online, I hoped to truly enjoy my first year of college life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The allocations went similarly for so many of us: get a rank, see where you fit, fill your preference and wait for the acceptance letter. In hindsight, it's amazing that such a small and short decision can influence your life's trajectory so much: it can change the people you interact with, the experiences you enjoy and the moments you cherish, but I'm getting existential at this point. I was now a student of IIT Delhi: I remember the first thing I did to show my allegiance was sketch the logo of IIT Delhi. Did you know there are 40 circles on the rim of the logo? Me neither :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the seat allocation rounds, the ball was finally set rolling: we got an email from IIT Delhi, asking us to register on their portal. Cue a long list of paperwork (there were more than 15 forms!), lots of running around and finally we were greeted with 'your documents are pending approval'. Kind of anticlimatic, but it would get better! Our online induction videos were uploaded on 11th November, and a lot of them were quite nice, especially the director's message. However, our department introduction video was conducted by a 2nd year and a 3rd year, and the department head was nowhere in sight (Bigger F for CS people, whose department introduction was not uploaded). We had a meeting with the Dean(s) on 12th, but because of technical glitches, it was postponed to 13th. Alright, that happens sometimes, I suppose. The meeting on 13th went ahead as planned, until the chat got spammed by a certain 'Watson'. The joys of an online semester, I chuckled and moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were split into two batches and forty groups, with groups 1-20 (Batch A) having a different set of courses for the first semester. We had our introductory classes from 16th-17th, with full classes scheduled to start from the 18th of November. Initially, social interaction with others from IITD was tricky: I hadn't attended a coaching and I knew absolutely no one at IIT Delhi from the first year. Fortunately, I was soon added to my department group, and I spent the first few days being moderately active there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time seemed to dilate from then on: the bogeys was loaded, the doors were shut, the train took off from the platform and the scenery outside dissolved to a blur. Classes took over, and fortunately we had some very good professors and a light workload in the start. I interacted with a few people personally (thanks to Teams chat), and joined a few discord servers, where people were active. Soon after (I don't remember the exact date), I was put into a hostel. Just like many other important things in life: where you're born, your name or your religion, your hostel is god-given (a 'lucky draw' if you're an atheist ;)). Fortunately, god smiled at me and gave me Udaigiri: the newest and largest hostel at IIT Delhi. Speaking to the handful of people I knew at that point, everyone was positive about Udaigiri, and the positivity was truly infectious. We were introduced to our ~Babloos~ BSW representatives soon after, and got to know a lot more about the culture of the hostel, and our exploits in dance and debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going into the next month, IITD came alive: In spite of the online semester, the six-day work week and the ever-rising workload, the seniors did their best to give the freshers a respite, a taste of what life at IITD was like, and for many of us freshies, it worked :) we had a tour of stalls sometime early in December, followed by BRCA night, where (for me) we had our first genuinely fun face-to-face interaction with our compatriots. Even though I'm not in touch with most of the people in my breakout room, it was a great experience. The Club groups opened soon after, and our introductory club events also started taking place. Having a background in Quizzing, Debating and Arts, those were the clubs whose events I took part in majorly, and I still remember my first debate speech, where I stalled for 30 seconds in the middle of a five minute speech :P. Things got serious soon after: we had our first quizzes scheduled in early and mid-December, and they were not pleasant. I think acclimatizing to the academic environment comes as a culture shock to all here, but it was still a culture shock nevertheless. The Maths quiz was easy-ish, but Chemistry was a nightmare. I got 17/25 in my first chemistry quiz while the highest was 23, and I was clueless for quite a few questions. This was quite the shock, and I realized that this journey would be harder than I thought. The Mechanics quiz went a bit better, but since that was out of 15 and easier, everyone did well comparatively. The only silver lining of the Chemistry quiz was that Prof. Kurur stayed on after the quiz to take doubts for the chemistry quiz, but soon we were peppering him with doubts about life, the universe and everything else, and he happily obliged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our minor examinations occured during the end of December. Barely knowing anyone forced me to spend most of my time studying, and it reflected: I got decent grades in all the papers except Mathematics (Ironic considering I had aptitude for my department, or so I believed). I was fortunate, for it didn't pan out that well for all of us: averages were low, most people cheated, a few were caught, and it was a low point for quite a few of us. I believe that the online sem exacerbated the testing scenario: giving an offline test is immensely easier than giving an online test. You have to deal with harder question papers, spotty internet connections, disturbances and sounds in your house and still answer all the questions asked in a span of less than two hours. This skewed the scenario heavily against the people with poor internet connections, or the ones with a not-so-quiet environment in their houses. While the institute was providing dongles and computer equipment to those affected, those were trying times; they still haven't ended, as I'll speak more about them up ahead, but let's return to the joys of the past for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after minors, things returned back to normal. This is the time when I believe fresher club interaction was at it's peak: I made most of my new friends in this phase, and most of them were from Quizzing Club. I would attend classes in the morning, take a nap in the afternoon, study for a while in the evening and babble about the weird and the wonderful with my friends on the myriad groups and clubs that had been created. Being an introvert like many others here, I finally began to fit in: the joys of a club are finding a group of people who resonate at the same frequency as you do, and I participated in a lot of quizzing events with them. There were quite a few events in this period as well: Literati, No Brainer, Potpourri, Quizzitch and a lot of other quizzes, which I enjoyed participating in. These took place in the middle of other quizzes as well, and juggling both academics and extracurriculars online was not great. I did mess up a quiz or two along the way (CML organic quiz I'm looking at you). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leading up to the majors, the discussion ebbed, and almost everyone returned back to studying. The majors were a make or break moment for a lot of people here, and you could sense the tension before them. Doubt groups that had been lying dormant suddenly became active, and Piazza, which nobody generally uses, started overflowing with doubts. People also started attending the academic mentorship programmes (which were quite helpful). It's said that the mind forgets bad memories more easily than good ones, and even though my majors went quite well, I can't remember what I did, or what I wrote in them (which is probably a good thing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post-major break was the best time for a lot of us. Covid was at a low, academics were out of everyone's mind, there were quite a few events to participate in, there were a lot of meetups across all the various cities and everyone was optimistic about returning to campus for the practical component of the second semester. However, the rest is history: Covid cases have spiked, institute elections have been postponed, students are being asked to return back to their homes and the situation has taken a turn for the worse. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was meant to be a light-hearted reminiscence about how life has been so far, but it's impossible to ignore what lies ahead. The only way to get through these trying times is positivity: stay positive. This is easier said than done, so here's a few things to do: pick up that guitar that's been gathering dust and pluck a few notes. Attend the next dance or music club workshop. Spend some time with your family members; play a game with your siblings. If you don't feel like doing these, remember that you're not alone! All of us at IITD are just a phone call or text away, so don't hesitate to pick up the phone and speak your mind out. We've been through times that have been harder than this, and given enough time this too will pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concluding on a positive note, I had to dig up my old calendars and schedule to write this; I haven't been completely honest if I ever mentioned that I remember it all, but there are a few moments that I do remember. I remember spending New Year with friends at IIT, playing skribbl till 1. I remember all the hostel, group and club meets that we had, most of which went on till late in the night. I remember the awkward silences online, where the TA would ask us if we understood the question, and everyone would stay quiet for 5 minutes. There are a lot of other things I will remember that I would rather not say here ;) A lot of people also feel sorry for us, saying that we won't have the memories that would be created were we on campus. I disagree. As John Milton said, "The mind is its own place, and in itself can make a heaven of hell, a hell of heaven", and though we may look back at these troubled times differently, we will cherish them nevertheless. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article featured in &lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wwS-bnfLO5CfsutfuD20Vf9QpdBPam2C/view?usp=sharing"&gt;Reverie&lt;/a&gt;, Udaigiri house's submission for Gazettale 2021.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Writing"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry><entry><title>This summer</title><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/articles/2021/this-summer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-06-16T20:18:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-06-16T20:18:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddha-deb.github.io,2021-06-16:/articles/2021/this-summer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What is a dream? all of us think of dreams as abstract ideals, far removed from reality, that we should chase with all the effort we can muster every day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditating on this a bit more, does this make sense? What is achieved by chasing an ideal when you can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What is a dream? all of us think of dreams as abstract ideals, far removed from reality, that we should chase with all the effort we can muster every day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditating on this a bit more, does this make sense? What is achieved by chasing an ideal when you can never reach it? also, what would you do if you reached the ideal? Would you just stop? Life would lose all it's meaning, and the only place to go then would be out of a tall window. How would you achieve this dream? It's one thing to dream of an ideal life, but quite another to actually achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to practicality, I believe that dreams are pointless. All life consists of are trajectories. This is somewhat similar to the 'life is but a journey through time' analogy, but I'll get to that in a moment. A trajectory is merely a path that you follow over a certain period of time. Where one trajectory ends, another begins. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would we do if we don't have a trajectory? Well, the readers of this article are certainly not dead, so it's natural to assume they're in one. Who decides this trajectory? I believe that this trajectory is a function of your starting parameters. In the universe of life, your starting position is completely random. We don't choose our family, our name, our religion, our sex or even the brand of diaper we poop in. When you're born, you begin as a tiny rock in the gravity well of your family, and our trajectories are basically the path this small rock will take over the course of it's lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rock in a universe analogy works fairly well philosophically: similar rocks get into similar trajectories. Consider the example of nature vs nurture: some rocks are born bigger, some smaller. Some are weirdly shaped, and some are perfect spheres. All rocks however will undergo collisions in their paths that make them what they are, and these collisions will be different depending on where in the universe they spawn. As RL Stevenson said, 'a man who, when born in London, makes a conscientious Protestant, would have made an equally conscientious Hindu if he had first seen daylight in Benares'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming to trajectories: rocks at similar potentials will traverse similar trajectories. A child born in Delhi will attend school in Delhi whereas a child born in Pune will attend school in Pune. One may point out the case when the Delhi kid's parents transfer to Pune, and I would say 'Well, the parent is bigger than the child, so the child would orbit the parent and go where the parent goes'. But enough of specifics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without getting into emotions right now (which would need their own framework, because emotions are amazingly complicated), what determines the 'quality' of a path? Does a longer trajectory mean better quality? What about one with fewer obstacles? Before long, we start questioning what it means to be 'happy', and then branch out into emotions, which as I said I couldn't model. For now, let's use a first approximation: a good trajectory is one which gives us a sense of accomplishment. In rockland, if we dodge or stabilise a rock around us without colliding with it and losing massive amounts of mass, we've accomplished something. The larger the rock we dodge or stabilize, the greater the accomplishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've done a terrible job of explaining that, but it suffices. The objective of our trajectory then is to give us the greatest feeling of accomplishment we can obtain, starting from our position in the universe. If we need to maximize accomplishment, then we would need to change our trajectory at times, which brings up the question: just how much control do we have over our trajectories?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm afraid this is the crux of the subject matter of this article, and I won't mind if you slept through the previous paragraphs. Many of us have our trajectories decided for us: go to school with your fellow rocks, then go to whichever college allows you to orbit it, then go to whichever company allows you to orbit it, then find another rock to orbit it with, so that your centre of mass is outside you and is preferably between both of you. Why? So that you can make more tiny rocks with the rock you paired up with. Then once your tiny little rocks have followed the same trajectory and your surface becomes more and more pockmarked with craters, spend your time reminiscing about what could have been. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thought that we can change our paths or stray off the beaten path almost seems alien: what would happen if we float out, with nothing to tether us to or to orbit around? What would happen if we face too much debris in the way, and are eventually reduced to stardust? The bigger question is "What if we could? Would you?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, something happens in the universe sending out wobbles of gravitational waves, and this was a major wobble, never seen before. A year back, I was sitting at home twiddling my thumbs. JEE had been postponed yet again, and I was at my wit's end, finding it amazingly hard to cope and losing motivation every day. Life back then was easy, when there was One trajectory to follow. One path to tread. One line to take. One singular goal. Now, I'm yet again twiddling my thumbs as my first year is at it's end. What's even more scary this time is that I realize I have no concrete goals. All I have are Passions. Dreams. No trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should consider myself fortunate: atleast I have my passions to work with. All that's left now is to chart my trajectory and follow it. What the next few years look like. What the next few chapters in my memoirs read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that's what I'm doing this summer.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Writing"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry><entry><title>The Last Time</title><link href="https://aniruddha-deb.github.io/articles/2021/last-time.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-05-29T14:43:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-05-29T14:43:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Aniruddha Deb</name></author><id>tag:aniruddha-deb.github.io,2021-05-29:/articles/2021/last-time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Soft sunlight streaked in through the curtains, illuminating the room in a warm glow. Of course, I noticed none of that. The only thing I was aware of was my phone's alarm clock ringing. After drowsily hitting the snooze button, I realized that I had done this twice already, so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Soft sunlight streaked in through the curtains, illuminating the room in a warm glow. Of course, I noticed none of that. The only thing I was aware of was my phone's alarm clock ringing. After drowsily hitting the snooze button, I realized that I had done this twice already, so I started scrolling through the notifications. It was 8:30, and my friends were abuzz with excitement. "Oh! The JEE Advanced results are coming out today!", I suddenly recalled while jumping out of bed, almost falling over in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next few moments were a blur as I got ready and had breakfast. I had given the JEE Advanced a while back, and was quite sure of a good rank in it. However, my father had fallen ill a few days after we came back from giving the exam. Initially thinking it was COVID, we got an RT-PCR test done, which came out to be negative. We then shrugged it off as a seasonal cold, and dad had been taking antibiotics and paracetamol and keeping well. At 55 years, he was a frail old man by now, and a heart patient, so it really pained my mother to see him ill. He was feeling worse than usual today, so he was not up when I was having breakfast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Baba kaise hai?" I asked Ma with my mouth stuffed full of paratha&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Kal raat unhe sardard hua tha. Ek aur COVID test karane ki soch rahe hai"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Accha. Aaj mera result aayega, and friends ke saath baahar party ka plan hai"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Ok. I would suggest you don't go, because Baba is really not keeping well"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about this for a while. I hadn't seen him, so I couldn't really comment. I was going insane staying inside the house, though. I hadn't been out anywhere after the JEE exams, and (quite obviously) before them as well. I was really aching to see my friends (and my girlfriend :P), and speak to them face to face. The network connection around our house didn't help either, and I couldn't speak to them properly or join the among us sessions that they used to hold regularly post JEE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Mumma, I really want to go. Please, bahut bore ho raha hoon ghar pe", I protested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma nodded silently for now. This was a common action for "We'll see", so I stayed quiet for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next hour was spent furiously chatting with my friends over WhatsApp, while the network connection permitted me to do so. All of us discussed our future plans: which IIT we intended to go to and which branch we would prefer. All of us had a fair idea of how our exam went, and most of us were doing quite well. My girlfriend was iffy on her decisions, and said that she would take a final decision only after her rank came out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the opportune moment came, and I tensely reloaded the page to see the result portal. With trembling hands, I typed my details in as Ma stood behind me reassuringly. I hesitated for a moment before clicking; should I check someone else's result first so that I can get an idea how mine will be? My parasympathetic nervous system took over, and I pressed the left mouse button. The page took a few seconds to load, and I skimmed through the information to finally come to my rank: 323. "Mixed feelings" would describe how I felt at that time; I wanted to get under 270, which would have gotten me into IITB EE. I doubted I would get CSE at an old 5 IIT with this rank; would probably have to settle for IITD MnC or IITR CSE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma was very happy; she embraced me and congratulated me, and went to tell Baba. I ran to my phone and saw the group; everyone had done slightly worse than they expected, but my girlfriend Swati still hadn't posted her marks. Strange, I thought. I sent her a personal message, which wasn't delivered immediately. Damn this spotty Internet! Slightly dejected, I went to see dad to inform him of the good news. I kept my distance from him, as he had asked me to do so. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Baba, I got 323"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though Ma had already told him the marks, he broke into a huge smile as I said them. He was very happy, happier than I've seen him in quite a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Shabash bete. You're truly independent now. Where do you plan on going?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"IIT Delhi Maths and Computing most probably, or IIT Roorkee Computer Science"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Good, good. No IITB? I think your friends were planning on going there"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"No, no IITB. Listen Baba, mai doston se milne jaa raha hoon ab. Pehle ka hi plan tha, we'll go to pavillion mall. I'll be back by evening most probably"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baba's face turned slightly pale. "Kidhar mat jaa", he croaked. "I might have COVID, and if I have it, you and your mother have it too. Don't spread it among others"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Nahi baba, you don't have it. Aaj test karaane kab jaa rahe ho?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Right now, by 12"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Don't worry, COVID nahi hai aapko. It's just some normal sickness and aap kaise bhi thode boodhe ho rahe ho"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He chuckled softly. "Beta sun, don't go anywhere. It's very risky."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was getting impatient by now. I had planned this for a long time, and I was getting impulsive after being bounded in these four walls for over 5 months. I resisted: "Baba please! I really want to go, bahut bore ho raha hoon! I don't even talk properly to my friends because signal nahi aati hai idhar! Just let me enjoy today, please, after getting my rank and results!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ma also took Baba's side, and firmly said "Vishnu, No! You're not going". Baba finally caved in. He was truly proud of my IIT marks, it seemed. With a smile, he replied "Nahi, jaane do usse. He's still a kid, let him enjoy now. Go, maze karke aao."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't expect Baba to cave in so quickly; he has a reputation of being very strict. I started to second guess myself. Maybe this is serious and he has COVID? Is he using negative psychology or something to get me to stay? Or is he really so happy with my marks? These thoughts evaporated as my phone pinged; Swati had texted me, "Can we talk when we meet?" I decided to go to the meet. I changed quickly and went to my parents' room, where I proclaimed "Ma, Baba, I'm going. Taking the Activa. Call if needed. See you!". Baba nodded with a smile and Ma said in a motherly fashion "Stay Safe!". &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached the mall by 11:30 and strolled in. Swati was already there, and so were some of my friends. I said hi, and asked her how her results were. She replied with a smile "You First!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Aw cmon, you must have checked the group for my marks"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Phir bhi, bol de"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"323"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friends let out a whoop of joy. Vedant said "Really? Tu itna accha kab ban gaya padhai me?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was laughing as well by now. After some more small talk, I finally got around to asking Swati her marks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Uh, 1302"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh nice, congrats! IIT Delhi Electrical milega tujhe with that rank!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Yeah, I guess"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Itni dukhi mat ho, I'm also going to IITD Maths and Computing most probably. We'll still be together"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She smiled back faintly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the day was a blur, as more friends came and we went over every minute detail of our lives during the lockdown; who got fat and who got thin and who got smarter, all was laid bare amid much laughter and camaderie. We finally got around to discussing where everyone was going, and everyone had a good idea of where they were going. A lot of us were going to IIT Delhi, so I realized that we'll all spend the next four years together as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we were done with our bickering, it was 6pm. Just as we were about to leave, Swati said "Can we stay for a few minutes more? I want to tell you something" All of our friends gave us the teenage grin, and I said "sure!" Once everyone had left and we had strolled around and made some more small talk, I asked her, "So what did you want to tell me?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I didn't get 1302"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh, Ok. What was your rank then?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"102"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could slowly feel the ground slipping out under me. I knew what this meant, but I put on a brave face for now and said "Wow, congrats! Why didn't you tell this to all of us then? 1302 kyun bolte gayi?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"You know I can't just do that! I was the weakest in our batch, the one who used to get the lowest marks in every test! How do you think everyone would feel if they found out I studied hard during the lockdown and jumped them? Do you feel happy that I got more than you even though you taught me 90% of what I know? Admit it!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silence followed. It took me a minute to gather up my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"So what are you doing now? I'm guessing it's IITB CSE for you then"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Yes. Girls quota ki wajah se mil jaayega, and my parents want me to go there as well"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was playing out like one of those clichéd romance tragedies. I played along and said "I can come to IITB! Mechanical mil jaayega mujhe, we can be together"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Forget it, Vishnu. You saw that everyone's going to Delhi, and you also want to go there."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn't deny this. I came back to reality, and an awkward silence followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I think it's best we break up. Long distance nahi ho paayega mujhse. We can still be friends"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's when the ground slipped out from under me; this was not happening. I asked her in anguish "Why don't you come to Delhi? IITD CSE is no less than IITB!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"My parents won't let me, they think Delhi is not a good place."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I'm ready to come to Bombay for you, but you're not coming to Delhi? After the three years we've been through together, all those times I taught you, all the times we went out, you're just..."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I choked up; I couldn't speak any more. I didn't have to. She completed the words for me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Well, I guess this is the last time we meet. Best of luck for whatever you do in life."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I nodded, and watched her walk away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I turned the other way and walked the mall a few times. It was relatively empty because of COVID, and I had the floors to myself and my thoughts. Stupidly, I realized that this was coming; there's a reason why teenage love is called puppy love, and I should have seen it earlier. There was no way our relationship would continue if she didn't need me academically, and I was too naïve to see that. I went through the five stages of grief all to quickly, blaming everyone from her parents to the girl quota, without which she would have come to Delhi. Eventually, I calmed down enough to ride my scooter home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I came home by 7:30, I realized that in haste, I had forgotten to take the house keys. "No Worries, Ma must have come back home" I thought as I rang the bell. No response. I waited for 5 minutes and rang the bell again. No response yet again. Frustrated, I spammed the bell. Once I finally accepted that my parents weren't home, I tried calling them, only for the cell phone signal to not reach them. I was cursing myself by now; what was a very happy day for everyone else was turning out to be my worst nightmare. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It struck me at once; they weren't back because dad had tested positive for COVID. Which meant that they were in one of the many hospitals in the city. This meant that I was also, in all probability, COVID positive. "Damnit" I cursed myself. I shouldn't ask my neighbours for help, in this case. In fact, there was nobody I could ask for help! I must have spread it to all my friends, and to Swati as well. This cooled the fire burning in me. Somewhat. My thoughts immediately turned to Baba and Ma; Baba was definitely not looking well today morning. Weary at the end of this long day, I sat down in front of the door, too mentally tired to go anywhere. I have been a lifelong atheist, but that was the only time I reached out to god with all the willpower I could muster, and asked him to save my father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was around 8 by the time I heard footsteps approaching me. I looked up and saw my uncle Jitendra; Uncle had already got COVID recently and he was now immune to it. I asked him "Uncle, Where is Baba? Why haven't they come home?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jitendra uncle sat down, and it was then that I realized his eyes were red and glazed over. He said softly, "Baba was waiting for a long time until he tested positive for COVID, and they had to shift him to hospital immediately. He had a heart attack at around 7:15, and didn't make it. Your Mummy was trying to call you but you were unreachable, so I decided to find you and tell you. I'm sorry."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story was originally written for BSP IIT Delhi's Muse magazine, but that 
hasn't been published yet :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCLAIMER:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a work of fiction. Unless otherwise indicated, all the names, characters, businesses, places, events and incidents in this book are either the product of the author's imagination or used in a fictitious manner. Any resemblance to actual persons, living or dead, or actual events is purely coincidental.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Writing"></category><category term="Writing"></category></entry></feed>