<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>General on Aniruddha Deb</title>
    <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/categories/general/</link>
    <description>Recent content in General on Aniruddha Deb</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 18:40:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/categories/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s easy to mess up</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2023/easy-to-mess-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 18:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2023/easy-to-mess-up/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s easy to mess up.
Of course. That&amp;rsquo;s what the title says. It seems like general advice, and making mistakes is part of life. You should &amp;ldquo;pick yourself up, brush yourself off and continue on your way!&amp;rdquo;
Not always.
Stubbing your toe on the couch is okay. Taking a major life decision on an impulse is not. Not choosing to back out of said decision even after multiple months have passed and the negative effects of that decision are evident in your life seems absurd, until you look around and realize that most people are doing this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intern Ashes</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2023/intern-ashes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 19:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2023/intern-ashes/</guid>
      <description>[If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read the previous article in this series, check out Intern Ignition]
In the weekends of my internship, and in the days that followed, I got to tour Europe a bit. What follows is a small travelogue of my experiences in these two months1,
Stroopwaffel Optiver gave us a goodie bag when we arrived, and among other things, it contained a box of Stroopwaffel!
Stroopwaffel are really thin waffles filled with caramel, and they taste amazing!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daft Punk and Interstella 5555</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/daft-punk-interstella/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2022 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/daft-punk-interstella/</guid>
      <description>In 2001, Daft Punk were nowhere near the mask-rocking superstars they are today. The only album they had to their credit was their debut, Homework, and their robot masks hadn&amp;rsquo;t even materialized yet. In 2001, they came out with Discovery, Which in many ways has defined their music style and approach for the 21st century.
The Importance of Discovery Daft Punk didn&amp;rsquo;t have their helmets before discovery.
Let that sink in.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Man Who Sold The World</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/man-who-sold-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 21:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/man-who-sold-the-world/</guid>
      <description>We passed upon the stair
We spoke of was and when
Although I wasn&amp;rsquo;t there
He said I was his friend
Which came as a surprise
I spoke into his eyes
&amp;ldquo;I thought you died alone,
A long long time ago&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Oh no, not me
I never lost control
You&amp;rsquo;re face to face
With the man who sold the world&amp;rdquo;
I laughed and shook his hand
And made my way back home</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cold Showers, Adulting and More</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/cold-showers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 09:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/cold-showers/</guid>
      <description>Day 249 of taking a cold shower. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing since April, and although the temperature has fallen and the geyser in my bathroom has been fixed come winter, it&amp;rsquo;s a habit I want to keep. Nothing makes you feel as alive as a cold shower does.
Speaking of durations, it&amp;rsquo;s also been exactly a month since my last post. A lot has happened since, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been too wrapped up in the happenings to get time to post here once a week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intern Inferno</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/intern-inferno/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/intern-inferno/</guid>
      <description>Not everything goes exactly as planned. That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s a plan, not a certainty.
Aiming in Before this entire joomla started, I asked myself: What is it I want from an intern?
I wanted to tour: I didn&amp;rsquo;t pick up a foreign research intern this summer, and was tired of hearing/seeing how others were roaming the world while I was scooping shuttles off the floor of my room. I wanted something that paid well: Apart from the feel-good factor, a good paying intern would put money for my masters&amp;rsquo; in the bank Above both of these:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Maneuvers and the Oberth Effect</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/orbital-oberth/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/orbital-oberth/</guid>
      <description>Once a rocket is in orbit, if it needs to change it&amp;rsquo;s orbit (either from a lower to a higher orbit, or from a circular to an elliptical orbit), it needs to execute an Orbital Maneuver. This is accomplished by using a small impulse from thrusters to change the tangential velocity, and hence slip into a different orbit as a consequence.
Types of Orbital Maneuvers There are two types of orbital maneuvers: the Hohmann transfer orbit and the Bi-elliptic transfer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leadership, among many other things</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/leadership/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 23:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/leadership/</guid>
      <description>Gazettale, BSP&amp;rsquo;s premier interhostel competition, for which our team worked day and night, recently released the final standings.
And we&amp;rsquo;re fifth.
Pop the champagne and dance, team, for we&amp;rsquo;re fifth!
Jokes aside, I&amp;rsquo;m lukewarm about the result. Proud of what a ragtag bunch of people came together and assembled in the span of around two weeks, but simultaneously disappointed for not reaching the lofty expectations we set of ourselves. Hindsight is 20/20 and often very saddening, for there is seldom joy in finding out what you couldn&amp;rsquo;t see earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freedom, Recaptured.</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/freedom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 17:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/freedom/</guid>
      <description>With the creation of my official website (safari butchers the CSS :/), I&amp;rsquo;ve now got more creative liberty and artistic freedom on the content I post here.
When I first made this blog, it used to be my own little corner of the internet. That changed once more people got to know about it, and I subconsciously put more pressure on myself to keep a strong technical background to whatever I post.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
