<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data on Aniruddha Deb</title>
    <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/tags/data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data on Aniruddha Deb</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 23:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aniruddhadeb.com/tags/data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LLMs for parsing unstructured data (IIT Course Planner v2!)</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2024/iit-course-planner-v2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 23:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2024/iit-course-planner-v2/</guid>
      <description>Happy new year! IIT Course planner (the course dependency graphs) used to be (and probably still is) the only reason people used to visit my blog. So much that it accounts for more views than any other webpage, except the homepage, and outdoes my next most popular article by 2x
The total pageviews is more than I expected :) It&amp;rsquo;s also no secret that I was working on a successor for the course planner for a while.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Wrangling in Practice: Dataset Creation from Poorly Structured Sources</title>
      <link>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/iit-course-planner-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2022 01:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aniruddhadeb.com/articles/2022/iit-course-planner-1/</guid>
      <description>I seldom get time to do anything other than course related activities nowadays, but in this midsem break, I did nothing other than roam around campus and laze in bed. And publish the first release of the IIT Delhi Course Planner Dataset (Also available on GitHub). This is a scraping of the IIT Delhi Courses of Study 2020-21, a behemoth 373-page PDF, which contains the course structure and information of all the Undergraduate and Postgraduate courses offered at IIT Delhi, and then some more.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
